[{
  "_id": {
    "$oid": "651556a04a8b33acb2b5b0cc"
  },
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "1. Which institution is to set up the ‘Corporate Debt Market Development Fund’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] RBI[B] SEBI[C] NSE[D] BSE"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [SEBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:SEBI decided to set up a corporate debt market development fund in the form of an Alternative Investment Fund.\nCorporate Debt Market Development Fund will be set up with an initial corpus of Rs 3,000 crore. It will function as a backstop facility for buying investment grade corporate debt securities during stressful times."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. ‘Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Voice’ is associated with which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] Australia[C] Greece[D] Italy"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Australia]",
      "hint": "Notes:First Peoples of Australia are people who lived in the Australia’s continental mainland and surrounding islands for tens of thousands of years before the arrival of first Europeans in the early 17th century.\nA referendum will be issued this year by the Australian government to alter the Constitution to recognise the First Peoples of Australia by establishing an Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Voice. It will decide whether these people should be formally consulted in the law making process."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. World Health Organisation (WHO) certified which countries as Malaria-free recently?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India and Sri Lanka[B] Azerbaijan and Tajikistan[C] Pakistan and Afghanistan[D] Nepal and Bangladesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Azerbaijan and Tajikistan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Recently, the World Health Organisation certified Azerbaijan and Tajikistan as Malaria-Free Countries.\nThey succeeded in eliminating the Anopheles mosquito-borne disease in their territories. In Tajikistan and Azerbaijan, the last cases of regional spread of Plasmodium vivax malaria were discovered in 2012 and 2014."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. IMF’s Extended Fund Facility has been reently approved for which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Pakistan[B] Afghanistan[C] Bangladesh[D] Ukraine"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Ukraine]",
      "hint": "Notes:The International Monetary Fund’s Extended Fund Facility is intended for countries experiencing serious medium-term BoP issues due to structural weakness that require time to address. It was recently approved for Ukraine to meet the urgent funding requirements amid the war with Russia."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. ‘Schengen area’ is associated with which association?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ISA[B] SAARC[C] G-20[D] European Union"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [European Union]",
      "hint": "Notes:The EU members have recently decided to digitize the Schengen Visa to make visa application process more efficient in Schengen area.\nThe Schengen area is a region comprising of 27 EU countries that have officially abolished all passports and other types of border control at their mutual borders."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Hexacentrus ashoka, which was seen in the news, belongs to which species?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Spider[B] Bush Cricket[C] Turtle[D] Snake"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Bush Cricket]",
      "hint": "Notes:Three new species of bush cricket was found recently. Two of these species (Hexacentrus tiddae and Hexacentrus ashoka) were found in Haryana. In the local dialect of Haryana, bush crickets are referred to as tiddaes.\nThe third species found in Meghalaya was named Hexacentrus khasiensis — after the Khasi hills where it was discovered."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Which country’s plant mycologist is the first person in the world to contract a plant fungal disease?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] China[C] Japan[D] USA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:‘Chondrostereum purpureum’ is a plant fungus that causes silver leaf disease in plants. A plant mycologist from India has become the first person in the world to contract a plant fungal disease.\nIt attacks most species of the rose family Rosaceae, particularly the genus Prunus. Among the millions of fungi present, only a few hundreds of fungi infect humans and animals."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. What is the GST collection recorded in the month of March?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Rs 1.5 lakh crore[B] Rs 1.6 lakh crore[C] Rs 1.8 lakh crore[D] Rs 2 lakh crore"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Rs 1.6 lakh crore]",
      "hint": "Notes:India’s Goods and Services Tax (GST) revenue collection for the month of March 2023 is stood at 1.6 lakh crore rupees.\nThis is 13 percent higher than the GST revenues in the same month of last year. It is for the fourth time, in the current financial year that the gross GST collection has crossed 1.5 lakh crore rupees, since the implementation of GST."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Which country launched the ‘Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] UK[C] Australia[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative was launched by the US to increase Ukraine’s capacity to defend itself from Russia’s aggression.\nUnder this initiative, USD 2.6 billion military aid package was announced by the US.  USAI is an authority under which the United States procures capabilities from industry."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. Which is the headquarters of the ‘Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC)’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Saudi Arabia[B] Israel[C] UAE[D] Pakistan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Saudi Arabia]",
      "hint": "Notes:Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) was founded in 1969 to protect the interests of the Muslim world.\nThe Indian government recently criticised the OIC after the organization’s secretariat issued statement alleging the targeting of Muslim community in several states during Ram Navami processions."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. Which country has invited Prime Minister to visit as a guest at the annual Bastille Day parade?",
      "options": [
        "[A] France[B] USA[C] Ukraine[D] Afghanistan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [France]",
      "hint": "Notes:France has invited Prime Minister Narendra Modi to visit Paris as a guest at the annual Bastille Day parade in July.\nThe Prime Minister and French President Emmanuel Macron are expected to discuss a number of major agreements including those on the Indo-Pacific region, nuclear power and defence, as the two countries mark the 25 th year of their strategic partnership."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. Which institution released the ‘World Energy Transitions: Outlook 2023’ report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] International Renewable Energy Agency[B] International Monetary Fund[C] World Bank[D] United Nations Environment Programme"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [International Renewable Energy Agency]",
      "hint": "Notes:The “World Energy Transitions: Outlook 2023” Report was released recently by the International Renewable Energy Agency.\nAccording to this report, while significant progress has been made towards increasing renewable energy generation, the global energy transition is still falling short of the 1.5°C pathway."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. Habrocestum togansangmai, a new species discovered, belongs to which species?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Spider[B] Snake[C] Turtle[D] Gecko"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Spider]",
      "hint": "Notes:Four new species of jumping spiders were recently discovered from the Meghalaya. One among them is ‘Habrocestum togansangmai’.\nIt is named after Garo freedom fighter Togan Sangma."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Union Information and Broadcasting Ministry signed agreement with which company to boost India’s creative economy?",
      "options": [
        "[A] IBM[B] Amazon India[C] Google[D] Microsoft"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Amazon India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Information and Broadcasting Ministry and Amazon India have signed a collaboration agreement in New Delhi to boost India’s creative economy and promote creative talent in the country.\nAs part of the agreement, Amazon Prime Video will sponsor scholarships, create internship programmes, and offer job opportunities for students of the Film and Television Institute of India (FTII) and Satyajit Ray Film and Television Institute."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The ‘Stand Up India Scheme’ has been extended till which year?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 2025[B] 2027[C] 2030[D] 2050"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [2025]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Stand up India Scheme was launched in 2016 to promote entrepreneurship focusing on economic empowerment and job creation. The scheme has been extended till 2025.\nOver Rs 40,700 crore was sanctioned under the Stand Up India Scheme over the seven years of its implementation. Around 80 percent of the loans under this scheme were provided to women."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. ‘Kudankulam Nuclear Power Project’ is located in which Indian state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Assam[B] Uttarakhand[C] Tamil Nadu[D] Odisha"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:Kudankulam Nuclear Power Project involves the setting up of India’ largest nuclear power station in Tirunelveli district of Tamil Nadu.\nA pressuriser was delivered for Reactor 5 of this power plant by AEM-Technologies Izhora, which is part of the machine-building division of Rosatom – Atomenergomash."
    },
    {
      "question": "17. Which country signed several economic agreements in energy, agriculture among other sectors, with China?",
      "options": [
        "[A] France[B] Germany[C] UK[D] Italy"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [France]",
      "hint": "Notes:France and China have signed several economic agreements involving major companies in sectors such as transport, energy, agriculture, culture and science during President Emmanuel Macron’s trip to China.\nOne of the deals will create a new assembly line in French aircraft manufacturer Airbus’ Tianjin factory so the company can double its production capacity of A320 models."
    },
    {
      "question": "18. UAE signed declaration with which country to begin talks on Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Vietnam[B] Israel[C] USA[D] Afghanistan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Vietnam]",
      "hint": "Notes:The United Arab Emirates (UAE) and Vietnam have signed a joint declaration of intent to launch talks on establishing a comprehensive economic partnership agreement (CEPA) between the two countries.\nThe UAE is Vietnam’s largest trade partner in the Arab countries, accounting for 39% of its total trade, and the volume of non-oil trade between the two countries reached USD 8 billion in 2022."
    },
    {
      "question": "19. ‘Prasthan Exercise’ the bi-annual coordinated exercise, held near which city in 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Chennai[B] Panjim[C] Mumbai[D] Kolkata"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Mumbai]",
      "hint": "Notes:Prasthan Exercise is a bi-annual coordinated exercise held among Indian defence, state and civilian agencies twice a year.\nIt was conducted recently in the offshore development area off Mumbai. It validates the measures to address contingencies that may occur in oil production platforms."
    },
    {
      "question": "20. Which Union Ministry appointed the ‘Committee on Digital Competition Law’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Finance[B] Ministry of Corporate Affairs[C] Ministry of External Affairs[D] Ministry of Corporate Affairs"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Ministry of Corporate Affairs]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Ministry of Corporate Affairs had appointed 10-Member Committee on Digital Competition Law, consisting of lawyers representing the Big Tech.\nIt is set to meet shortly to discuss provisions of the draft Digital Competition Law. The committee is responsible for examining the need for an ex-ante regulatory mechanism for digital markets via a separate legislation."
    },
    {
      "question": "21. ‘Tropospheric Emissions Monitoring of Pollution Instrument’ is a device of which space agency?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ISRO[B] NASA[C] ESA[D] JAXA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [NASA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Tropospheric Emissions Monitoring of Pollution Instrument is a new NASA device that will track pollution over North America.\nIt will enable scientists to monitor air pollutants and their sources from space. The spectrometer designed to measure air pollution across greater North America at a high resolution and on an hourly basis."
    },
    {
      "question": "22. ‘AlUla Declaration’, which was seen in the news, is related to which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Russia[B] Qatar[C] Israel[D] Iran"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Qatar]",
      "hint": "Notes:A fourth joint meeting between the delegates of the UAE and Qatar was held in Abu Dhabi to follow up on the implementation of the AlUla Declaration.\nThe AlUla Declaration, which was signed in 2021, resolved the dispute with Qatar and called for unity and the strengthening of relations among GCC countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "23. Which NBFC firm has raised USD 750 million through issuance of green bonds?",
      "options": [
        "[A] REC[B] PFC[C] Bajaj Finance[D] Aditya Birla Finance"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [REC]",
      "hint": "Notes:State-owned non-banking finance firm REC recently raised USD 750 million through issuance of green bonds\nThe net proceeds from the issue of the bonds will be applied to finance, in whole or in part, the eligible green projects in accordance with the approvals granted by the Reserve Bank of India from time to time and in accordance with the ECB guidelines."
    },
    {
      "question": "24. Which state/UT launched the ‘Directorate of Paribar’  to have better connect with the people of the state within country and across the world?",
      "options": [
        "[A] West Bengal[B] Odisha[C] Andhra Pradesh[D] Karnataka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Odisha]",
      "hint": "Notes:The establishment of the Directorate of Odisha Paribar was approved recently by the state cabinet. It will be the one-stop point of contact and support system for Odias dwelling in other parts of India and across the world.\nThe Directorate of Odisha Parivar will be under the Department of Odia Language, Literature and Culture to have better connect with Pravasi Odias within the country and across the world."
    },
    {
      "question": "25. As per the 5th Cycle of India’s Tiger Census, how many tigers are in India, as of 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 1167[B] 2167[C] 3167[D] 4167"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [3167]",
      "hint": "Notes:The 5th Cycle of India’s Tiger Census was released recently by Prime Minister Modi. This census revealed that India’s tiger population stands at 3,167 in the wild.\nThis figure is 200 more than it had four years ago. India is estimated to have more than 70% of the world’s tigers."
    },
    {
      "question": "26. Dogri language is prevalently spoken in which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] West Bengal[B] Assam[C] Jammu and Kashmir[D] Telangana"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:Dogri is an Indo-Aryan language primarily spoken in the Jammu region of Jammu and Kashmir. Union Minister of Law, Justice and Parliamentary Affairs, Kiren Rijiju released the first edition of the Dogri version of the Constitution of India at University of Jammu.\nDogri language was added in the 8th Schedule of the Constitution back in 2003."
    },
    {
      "question": "27. As per a recent report of the NSO, what per centage of communicable disease deaths in 2021 was due to respiratory ailments?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 18 %[B] 38 %[C] 58 %[D] 78 %"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [78 %]",
      "hint": "Notes:As per the latest data released by National Statistical Office (NSO), the share of respiratory infections in deaths caused by communicable diseases rose by 10 per cent to 78 per cent in 2021 from 68 per cent in 2020,\nThis means about four out of five deaths due to communicable diseases were caused by the respiratory ailments."
    },
    {
      "question": "28. Which city is the host of the ‘Third Regional Symposium on Greening the Judiciaries’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] New York[B] Nairobi[C] New Delhi[D] Dhaka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Nairobi]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Third Regional Symposium on Greening the Judiciaries in Africa was organized by the Africa Judicial Education Network on Environmental Law (AJENEL) in Nairobi, Kenya.\nIt was held based on the theme ‘Strengthening the Role of Judiciaries in Addressing Climate Change in Africa’."
    },
    {
      "question": "29. Which state/UT has organised the ‘Baisakhi Mahotsav 2023’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Andhra Pradesh[B] Jammu and Kashmir[C] Kerala[D] Odisha"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:Baisakhi Mahotsav 2023 will be organized by Jammu’s Directorate of Tourism. The event celebrates Dogra culture and heritage.\nBaisakhi, also known as Vaisakhi, is one of the harvest festivals celebrated in India and in parts of the world largely by the Sikh community."
    },
    {
      "question": "30. Which Indian chess player has won the World Chess Armageddon Asia & Oceania?",
      "options": [
        "[A] R Praggnanandhaa[B] D Gukesh[C] Arjun Erigaisi[D] Nihal Sarin"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [D Gukesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Teenaged Indian Grandmaster D Gukesh stunned former world rapid champion Nodirbek Abdusattorov of Uzbekistan in the final to win the World Chess Armageddon Asia & Oceania.\nThe 16-year-old Indian won in a field that included former world classical champion Vladimir Kramnik, Daniil Dubov, Yangyi Yu (China), Vidit Gujrathi and Karthikeyan Murali (both India) and Param Maghsoodloo (Iran), apart from Abdusattorov."
    },
    {
      "question": "31. ‘Experimental Advanced Superconducting Tokamak (EAST) fusion energy reactor’ is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] China[C] USA[D] UAE"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [China]",
      "hint": "Notes:Experimental Advanced Superconducting Tokamak (EAST) fusion energy reactor is located in Hefei, China.\nThe reactor has set a new record by creating an artificial sun that sustained plasma for 403 seconds. This broke the 2017 record of 101 seconds."
    },
    {
      "question": "32. ‘Pohela Boishakh’ marks the beginning of the new year in which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Odisha[B] West Bengal[C] Uttarakhand[D] Meghalaya"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [West Bengal]",
      "hint": "Notes:Pohela Boishakh, also known as Bengali New Year, is a significant cultural festival in Bangladesh and the Bengali-speaking states of India including West Bengal.\nThe festival is celebrated on the first day of the Bengali calendar, which usually falls in the month of April. This year, it is celebrated on April 15."
    },
    {
      "question": "33. Which bloc has set up a set up a task force to monitor OpenAI’s ChatGPT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] SAARC[B] EU[C] ASEAN[D] G-20"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [EU]",
      "hint": "Notes:The European Data Protection Board is an autonomous institute in charge of supervising data protection regulations within the European Union.\nIt has recently decided to set up a task force to monitor Open AI’s ChatGPT. Italy last month imposed a temporarily ban on ChatGPT."
    },
    {
      "question": "34. The ‘Bharat Gaurav Tourist train’ was flagged off to mark birth anniversary of which leader in April?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Jawaharlal Nehru[B] Dr B R Ambedkar[C] Subash Chandra Bose[D] Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Dr B R Ambedkar]",
      "hint": "Notes:Union Tourism Minister G Krishan Reddy and Social Justice and Empowerment Minister Dr. Virendra Kumar flagged off Bharat Gaurav Tourist train to mark the birth anniversary of Dr B R Ambedkar from New Delhi.\nGovernment has developed Panchteerth, five place associated with Dr Ambedkar. During the 8-day tour, the train will cover cities including, New Delhi, Mhow, Nagpur, Varanasi and sacred Buddhist sites like Sanchi, Sarnath, Gayaand Rajgir and Nalanda."
    },
    {
      "question": "35. ‘Nagarjunasagar-Srisailam Tiger Reserve’ is located in a region spanning across which states?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Tamil Nadu- Kerala[B] Andhra Pradesh -Telangana[C] Andhra Pradesh- Tamil Nadu[D] Maharashtra- Karnataka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Andhra Pradesh -Telangana]",
      "hint": "Notes:Nagarjunasagar-Srisailam Tiger Reserve is the largest tiger reserve in India, spanning across Andhra Pradesh and Telangana.\nTo ensure smooth traffic flow, the National Highways Authority of India (NHAI) has enabled FASTag-based payments at forest entry points across Nagarjunasagar-Srisailam Tiger Reserve (NSTR)."
    },
    {
      "question": "36. ‘Cheiraoba’ is a festival celebrated in which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Tripura[B] Andhra Pradesh[C] Maharashtra[D] Manipur"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Manipur]",
      "hint": "Notes:Cheiraoba is considered to be one of the most important festivals of Manipur and it marks the beginning of the lunar new year for the people of Meitei community of Manipur and across the globe.\nThe festival is also called as Sajibu Nongma Pānba which means “First day of Sajibu Month”."
    },
    {
      "question": "37. What is ‘RAMBAAN’, which was recently seen in the news?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Elephant Species[B] Mobile Clinic[C] COVID vaccine[D] Launch Vehicle"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Mobile Clinic]",
      "hint": "Notes:RAMBAAN (Rapid Action Mobile BSL3+ Advanced Augmented Network) is India’s first mobile BSL-3 laboratory.\nIt was showcased at the second G20 Health Working Group Meeting, which was organized in Goa. This fully equipped, Made-in-India mobile clinic can reach remote regions to conduct testing."
    },
    {
      "question": "38. Which institution launched the ‘State of World Population’ Report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UNICEF[B] UNFPA[C] WEF[D] IMF"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [UNFPA]",
      "hint": "Notes:The State of World Population report titled ‘8 Billion Lives, Infinite Possibilities’ was released recently by the United Nations Population Fund.\nAccording to this report released by UNFPA, India is now the most populous country in the world, as it has surpassed China’s population numbers."
    },
    {
      "question": "39. Scientists of which institution have recently identified Electromagnetic Ion Cyclotron (EMIC) waves?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indian Space Research Organisation[B] IIT – Madras[C] Indian Antarctic station[D] National Institute of Ocean Technology"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Indian Antarctic station]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Scientists of Indian Antarctic station, Maitri, have recently identified and studied the characteristics of Electromagnetic Ion Cyclotron (EMIC) waves, which are a form of plasma waves.\nThese waves are said to play an important role in precipitation of killer electrons (electrons having speed close to speed of light, which form the radiation belt of planet Earth), which are hazardous to our space-borne technology and instruments."
    },
    {
      "question": "40. ‘Hanuman Plover Bird’ is a species endemic to which countries?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India and Sri Lanka[B] USA and Canada[C] Australia and New Zealand[D] Japan and Indonesia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [India and Sri Lanka]",
      "hint": "Notes:Hanuman Plover Bird has been reinstated as species after more than eight decades. This bird is endemic to India and Sri Lanka.\nHanuman Plover Bird was merged with the Kentish plover in the 1930s as both species were considered to be the same."
    },
    {
      "question": "41. Which institution released the ‘The State of the World’s Children 2023: For Every Child, Vaccination’ report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UNICEF[B] NITI Aayog[C] Women and Child Development Ministry[D] Pratham Foundation"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [UNICEF]",
      "hint": "Notes:‘The State of the World’s Children 2023: For Every Child, Vaccination’ report was released recently by the UNICEF India.\nAccording to this report, India is one of the countries with highest vaccine confidence in the world. The popular perception of the importance of vaccines for children held firm or improved only in China, India and Mexico out of 55 countries studied."
    },
    {
      "question": "42. ‘Safe Kerala Project’ which was launched recently, aims to minimise?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Honour Killings[B] Road Accidents[C] Covid Deaths[D] Cardiac Arrests"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Road Accidents]",
      "hint": "Notes:The state government of Kerala launched the Safe Kerala Project to minimize the number of on-road accidents and prevent traffic violations in the state.\nAs part of this project, Artificial Intelligence-based cameras will be used to identify traffic violations and impose fines."
    },
    {
      "question": "43. ‘Mission Youth’, which received the PM Award for Excellence under Innovation Category, is from which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Karnataka[B] Jammu and Kashmir[C] Odisha[D] Jharkhand"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Jammu and Kashmir administration’s flagship initiative, ‘Mission Youth’ recently received the Prime Minister’s Award for Excellence under the Innovation (state) category.\nIt is a unique programme aimed at empowering youth in the union territory. The mission will focus on all individuals between the age of 15 to 35 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "44. Fort Dansborg (Danish Fort), which was seen in the news, is located in which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kerala[B] Tamil Nadu[C] Odisha[D] Maharashtra"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:Fort Dansborg, also known as the Danish Fort, was built in 1620 at the eastern coastal village of Tharangambadi.\nThe Tamil Nadu state tourism department has sanctioned Rs.3 crore to conduct various infrastructure development works at this fort."
    },
    {
      "question": "45. Who is the first woman IAF officer to receive a gallantry medal?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Avani Chaturvedi[B] Bhawana Kant[C] Deepika Misra[D] Mohana Singh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Deepika Misra]",
      "hint": "Notes:Wing Commander Deepika Misra recently became the first woman Indian Air Force (IAF) officer to receive a gallantry medal.\nShe received Vayu Seva Medal for gallantry from Indian Air Force chief Air Chief Marshal VR Chaudhari recently."
    },
    {
      "question": "46. Which Indian Armed Force acquired the ‘Nagastra 1’ an indigenous drone developed in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indian Army[B] Indian Navy[C] Indian Air Force[D] Indian Coast Guard"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Indian Army]",
      "hint": "Notes:Nagastra 1 is an indigenous drone developed by the Economic Explosives Limited. It was acquired recently by the Indian Army to increase its operations at the LOC.\nNagastra 1 can strike targets within 15-30 km, using GPS-enabled precision. It is also designed to loiter over enemy territory in search of moving personnel, military vehicles or an enemy position before being taken down."
    },
    {
      "question": "47. Which case is famous for the definition of basic structure of the Indian Constitution?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kesavananda Bharati Case[B] Romesh Thappar Case[C] Shreya Singhal Case[D] Vishakha V Case"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Kesavananda Bharati Case]",
      "hint": "Notes:Kesavananda Bharati Case is a landmark case where the Supreme Court defined the basic structure of the Indian Constitution. The judgement for this case was delivered on April 24, 1973.\nThe case is also known as the Fundamental Rights Case. The Supreme Court asserted its right to strike down amendments to the constitution that were in violation of the fundamental architecture of the constitution."
    },
    {
      "question": "48. When is the ‘National Panchayati Raj Day’ celebrated?",
      "options": [
        "[A] April 20[B] April 22[C] April 24[D] April 26"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [April 24]",
      "hint": "Notes:‘National Panchayati Raj Day’ is celebrated every year on April 24. The Ministry of Panchayati Raj in collaboration with the state Government of Madhya Pradesh is commemorating National Panchayati Raj Day in Madhya Pradesh as part of Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav – Samaaveshi Vikaas (Inclusive Development).\nThe Prime Minister was the Chief Guest at the national function."
    },
    {
      "question": "49. Which country recently released the ‘Indo-Pacific Outlook’ document?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Sri Lanka[C] Bangladesh[D] Nepal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Bangladesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Bangladesh officially unveiled its Indo-Pacific Outlook (IPO) outlining four guiding principles and 15 objectives in the document.\nIt recognizes the importance of stability and prosperity in the Indo-Pacific for achieving Bangladesh’s Vision 2041."
    },
    {
      "question": "50. ‘Mohammed Shahabuddin’ recently became the President of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Nepal[B] Bangladesh[C] UAE[D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Bangladesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Mohammed Shahabuddin is a veteran freedom fighter, jurist and politician. He recently became the 22nd President of Bangladesh.\nShahabuddin succeeds Abdul Hamid whose tenure ended recently. He was elected as president unopposed in February this year as a candidate of the ruling Awami League."
    }
  ],
  "type": "current-affairs-quiz-april-2023",
  "__v": 0
},
{
  "_id": {
    "$oid": "651556a14a8b33acb2b5b0ce"
  },
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "1. Spheroidal carbonaceous particle is a component of?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Fly Ash[B] Saw Dust[C] Dry Ice[D] Common Salt"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Fly Ash]",
      "hint": "Notes:Spheroidal carbonaceous particle (SCP) is a component of fly ash and is a by-product of industrial high-temperature combustion of coal and fuel-oil.\nRecently, researchers from British Antarctic Survey and the University College London, for the first time identified SCP in an Antarctic ice core. The sample dated back to 1936, indicating physical markers of fossil fuel combustion have been trapped in ice layers for decades."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. When is the ‘World Intellectual Property Day’ observed?",
      "options": [
        "[A] April 24[B] April 26[C] April 28[D] April 30"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [April 26]",
      "hint": "Notes:The World Intellectual Property Day is observed every year on April 26. It raises global awareness about intellectual properties and their protection.\nThe WIPO convention came into effect in 1970 and, in the year 2000, WIPO’s member states declared April 26 as World Intellectual Property."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Scientists from which country have developed ‘Mobile Vaccine Printer’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] USA[C] Russia[D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Mobile vaccine printer is an innovative technology developed by researchers at MIT. This small device is capable of producing hundreds of vaccine doses within a single day.\nIt has the potential to provide vital vaccines to individuals in remote regions who lack the required resources for conventional vaccine storage and transportation."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Which institution released a report on ‘Contribution of terrestrial animal source food to healthy diets’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] FAO[B] NITI Aayog[C] ICAR[D] ICRISAT"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [FAO]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) recently released a report titled “Contribution of terrestrial animal source food to healthy diets for improved nutrition and health outcomes”.\nAccording to this report, animal food products like meat, eggs and milk can help achieve global nutrition targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. Which country has recorded an increase in cases of ‘Klebsiella pneumoniae bacteria’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] China[C] USA[D] North Korea"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Klebsiella pneumoniae is a gram-negative, lactose-fermenting bacterium capable of causing destruction to the human and animal lungs.\nThere has been an increase in the number of cases of individuals infected with the Klebsiella pneumoniae in Seattle, US."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which country is supplying Mi-17 helicopter engines and auxiliary spare parts to Pakistan?",
      "options": [
        "[A] China[B] Pakistan[C] Russia[D] Ukraine"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Ukraine]",
      "hint": "Notes:Ukraine is launching the process of supplying the Mi-17 helicopter engines and auxiliary spare parts to Pakistan military. Mi-17 is a Soviet-designed military helicopter used for carrying personnel, cargo and equipment.\nPakistan will export three consignments of 155 mm artillery ammunition rounds over the next three months to Ukraine."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Which is the governing body of the Department of Atomic Energy in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Atomic Energy Commission of India[B] NITI Aayog[C] Department of Space[D] DRDO"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Atomic Energy Commission of India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Atomic Energy Commission of India is the governing body of the Department of Atomic Energy. Recently, BARC Director Ajit Kumar Mohanty was appointed as the chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission and the Secretary of the Department of Atomic Energy."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. ‘Sinthan Festival’ was organised in which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Jammu and Kashmir[B] Assam[C] West Bengal[D] Karnataka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:The two-day maiden Sinthan Festival was organized recently by the Directorate of Tourism, Jammu in collaboration with the District Administration Kishtwar, Indian Army and Jammu and Kashmir Academy of Art, Culture and Languages.\nThis festival was held in Kishtwar District of Chenab Valley."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Which state/UT announced a ‘Summer Action Plan’, which involves the participation of 30 government departments?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Rajasthan[B] New Delhi[C] Chhattisgarh[D] Punjab"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [New Delhi]",
      "hint": "Notes:Delhi Chief Minister recently announced a ‘Summer action plan’ to combat air pollution during summer months. It involves the participation of 30 government departments.\nThe primary focus of the action plan is on dust pollution, which has been a major contributor to the city’s worsening air quality."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. Liberica excelsa, which was seen in the news, belongs to which species?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Tea[B] Coffee[C] Rice[D] Wheat"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Coffee]",
      "hint": "Notes:Liberica excelsa is a species of coffee that is found to be capable of withstanding heat, drought and disease exacerbated by global warming.\nIt is being promoted by large coffee exporting countries in Africa as an alternative to Arabica and robusta, which are at risk to climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. King Charles III, who was officially crowned recently, wore which crown?",
      "options": [
        "[A] St John’s Crown[B] St Edward’s Crown[C] St Charles’ Crown[D] St Stephen’s Crown"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [St Edward’s Crown]",
      "hint": "Notes:King Charles III, who was officially crowned alongside Queen Camilla, wore St Edward’s Crown for the historic coronation ceremony.\nThe 74-year-old royal was officially crowned the UK’s monarch at Westminster Abbey. It is tradition for the monarch to wear the solid gold St Edward’s Crown. The crown dates back hundreds more years – to 1661 when it was made for King Charles II."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. As per the ‘Internet in India Report, what percent of the Indian population accessed the internet at least once a month in 2022?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 22 %[B] 32 %[C] 42 %[D] 52 %"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [52 %]",
      "hint": "Notes:Internet in India Report 2022 was released recently by the Internet and Mobile Association of India (IAMAI) and Kantar.\nAccording to this report, around 52 percent of the Indian population accessed the internet at least once a month in 2022."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. Which Union Ministry organised an outreach program called ‘BizAmp’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of MSME[B] Ministry of Commerce and Industry[C] Ministry of External Affairs[D] Ministry of Sports and Youth Affairs"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of MSME]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Union Ministry of MSME collaborated with NSIC Venture Capital Fund Limited (NVCFL) to organize an outreach program called BizAmp in Dimapur, Nagaland.\nThe main objective of this program was to empower MSMEs in the North Eastern States and help them amplify their businesses by utilizing the benefits provided under the Self-Reliant India (SRI) Fund."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. ‘Vaisakh Purnima’ is associated with which religion?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Hinduism[B] Jainism[C] Buddhism[D] Jainism"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Buddhism]",
      "hint": "Notes:Vaisakh Purnima is celebrated on 5th May this year. The Union Ministry of Culture will collaborate with the International Buddhist Confederation (IBC) to celebrate this occasion at the National Museum in New Delhi.\nSeveral programmes will be organised in Delhi and across the country to mark the ‘UN Day of Vesak’."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. Which institution released the “Is an End to Child Marriage Within Reach?” report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UNESCO[B] UNICEF[C] NITI Aayog[D] WEF"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [UNICEF]",
      "hint": "Notes:UNICEF recently released a report titled ‘Is an End to Child Marriage Within Reach?’. According to this report, while the rate of child marriage is declining, it is not enough.\nThe present rate would mean that the practice will continue to exist for 300 more years. About 640 million girls, teens and women were victims of the practice of child marriage."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Which institution along with Bank for International Settlements (BIS) launched ‘G20 TechSprint’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UIDAI[B] RBI[C] SEBI[D] NITI Aayog"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [RBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:Reserve Bank of India (RBI) and Bank for International Settlements (BIS) launch G20 TechSprint, a global technology competition.\nTechSprint will focus on developing innovative technology solutions for cross-border payments. The competition is open for developers around the world."
    },
    {
      "question": "17. How many members are present in the high level committee constituted for Restructuring of ICAR?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 5[B] 7[C] 10[D] 11"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [11]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Government of India has set up a 11-member high-level committee to restructure the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR). The committee will be under the chairmanship of the Additional Secretary of the Department of Agricultural Research and Education and Secretary of ICAR.\nThe committee has been constituted to make recommendations for rationalising and right-sizing the 94-year-old ICAR."
    },
    {
      "question": "18. MoHUA has signed a MoU with which organisation, for technical assistance under the Swachh Bharat Mission-Urban 2.0?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ISRO[B] DRDO[C] RITES[D] Indian Army"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [RITES]",
      "hint": "Notes:Ministry of Housing and Urban Affairs (MoHUA) signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with RITES Limited for technical assistance for Solid Waste Management (SWM) & Used Water Management UWM under Swachh Bharat Mission-Urban 2.0.\nUnder this MoU, RITES will help standardise processes and design facilities for solid waste and used water management in towns with a population of below 1 lakh."
    },
    {
      "question": "19. Which is the first state to provide digital health cards for children?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Uttar Pradesh[B] Assam[C] West Bengal[D] Rajasthan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Uttar Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:The School Health Program was launched recently by the Urban Development Department and Lucknow Smart City.\nThis initiative makes Uttar Pradesh the first state in the country to provide digital health cards for children."
    },
    {
      "question": "20. Which military unit is an auxiliary organization with part-time volunteers, who assist the Indian Army?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Territorial Army[B] Friends of Army[C] Friends of People[D] Border Volunteers"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Territorial Army]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Territorial Army, a military unit in India, is an auxiliary organization with part-time volunteers who provide assistance to the Indian Army.\nDefence Minister Rajnath Singh recently approved the posting of women officers of the TA with Engineer Regiments along the LOC and as staff officers at TA Group Headquarters/ Directorate General of Territorial Army at New Delhi."
    },
    {
      "question": "21. ‘Operation Trinetra’ was conducted in which state/ UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] West Bengal[B] Uttarakhand[C] Jammu and Kashmir[D] Punjab"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:Operation Trinetra is a massive search operation that was launched to hunt down terrorists in Jammu and Kashmir’s Rajouri.\nDuring this operation, a total of five soldiers lost their lives. It was conducted by the Indian Army along with the Central Reserve Police Force (CRPF) and Jammu and Kashmir Police."
    },
    {
      "question": "22. What is ‘Cordyceps Sinensis’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Caterpillar[B] Fungus[C] Virus[D] Bacterium"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Fungus]",
      "hint": "Notes:Cordyceps Sinensis, locally called yarchagumba, is a parasitic fungus that grows on the body of a caterpillar.\nIt is harvested by villagers in Nepal and Tibet to be sold in neighbouring China, where it is used in herbal medicines."
    },
    {
      "question": "23. ‘PMJJBY, PMSBY and APY’ were launched in which year?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 2015[B] 2017[C] 2019[D] 2020"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [2015]",
      "hint": "Notes:Pradhan Mantri Suraksha Bima Yojana (PMJJBY), Pradhan Mantri Jeevan Jyoti Bima Yojana (PMSBY) and Atal Pension Yojana (APY) have completed eight years. They were launched in 2015.\nTill date, PMJJBY recorded more than 16 crore enrolments, PMSBY recorded more than 34 crore enrolments and APY recorded around 5 crore subscribers."
    },
    {
      "question": "24. Which Union Ministries organised the ‘ECHO Exhibition’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Women and Child Development-External Affairs Ministry[B] Health and Family Welfare- MSME Ministry[C] Jal Shakti- Housing and Urban Affairs Ministry[D] Home Affairs- Defence Ministry"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Women and Child Development-External Affairs Ministry]",
      "hint": "Notes:ECHO (Economy with safe climate and health leads to greater opportunities) exhibition was organized by the Ministry of Women and Child Development in collaboration with the Ministry of External Affairs.\nIt was organized at the sidelines of the 3rd Development Working Group (DWG) meeting of G-20."
    },
    {
      "question": "25. Which space agency has developed the ‘Aeolus Satellite’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] JAXA[B] ISRO[C] NASA[D] ESA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [ESA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Aeolus Satellite is one of the most effective weather satellites developed by the ESA. It is currently on a trajectory to return to Earth’s atmosphere.\nAeolus, an Earth Explorer research mission, was designed to demonstrate new space technology. The 1360-kilogram satellite is on its way to crash on the planet."
    },
    {
      "question": "26. Which country is set to provide 1.2 billion USD more to Ukraine as a part of its Security Assistance Initiative?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] Israel[C] UAE[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:As part of the Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative, the US will provide 1.2 billion USD more in long-term military aid to Ukraine.\nIt will help Kyiv strengthen its air defences against Russia’s attacks."
    },
    {
      "question": "27. IIT Madras has developed the ‘Piezoelectric MEMS Technology’, along with which institution?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ISRO[B] DRDO[C] BARC[D] CDAC"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [DRDO]",
      "hint": "Notes:The piezoelectric MEMS technology has been jointly developed by researchers at DRDO and IIT Madras.\nThis sensor technology has the potential to be used for underwater communications by the Indian Navy."
    },
    {
      "question": "28. Which racing driver won the Miami Grand Prix title in 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Charles Leclerc[B] Max Verstappen[C] Sergio Perez[D] Lewis Hamilton"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Max Verstappen]",
      "hint": "Notes:Max Verstappen won the Miami Grand Prix from ninth on the starting grid, with the fastest lap.\nMexica’s Perez came second while Fernando Alonso came third. Verstappen was also the winner of last year’s inaugural Miami Grand Prix."
    },
    {
      "question": "29. Which Union Ministry launched the ‘Harit Sagar Guidelines 2023’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Jal Shakti[B] Ministry of Ports, Shipping and Waterways[C] Ministry of External Affairs[D] Ministry of Commerce and Industry"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of Ports, Shipping and Waterways]",
      "hint": "Notes:Harit Sagar Guidelines 2023 was unveiled recently by the Ministry of Ports, Shipping and Waterways. It envisions Ecosystem Dynamics in port development, operation and maintenance.\nIt lays emphasis on use of Clean / Green energy in Port operation, developing Port capabilities for storage, handling and bunkering Greener Fuels."
    },
    {
      "question": "30. Fossil remains of a giant pilosaur was discovered in which country recently?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] China[C] England[D] Japan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [England]",
      "hint": "Notes:Fossil remains of a giant pilosaur was discovered in England recently. Pilosaur is a marine reptile that was a distant cousin of modern turtles.\nFossilised bones from the gigantic sea creature that lived 150 million years ago have been found in a drawer at Oxfordshire’s Abingdon County Hall Museum."
    },
    {
      "question": "31. ‘RAMP programme’ is associated with which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Textiles[B] Ministry of MSME[C] Ministry of Power[D] Ministry of Culture"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of MSME]",
      "hint": "Notes:The RAMP programme aims at improving access to market and credit of MSMEs, improving Centre-State linkages and addressing issues of delayed payments of MSMEs.\nThe first meeting of the National MSME Council was organized by the MSME ministry. It was set up to function as an administrative body that oversee coordination between central ministries/departments, and monitor progress on reforms including the RAMP programme."
    },
    {
      "question": "32. ‘OFDA 4000’ is a state-of-art equipment, which has been procured by which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Arunachal Pradesh[B] Jammu and Kashmir[C] Rajasthan[D] Gujarat"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:The OFDA 4000 is a cutting-edge equipment capable of testing the authenticity of Pashmina. It was procured recently by Handicrafts and Handloom Department Kashmir.\nThe equipment is capable of testing more than 40000 fibres in less than a minute and can determine such characteristics of the fibre."
    },
    {
      "question": "33. Which Union Ministry launched a learning management information system -SAKSHAM?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of MSME[B] Ministry of Health and Family Welfare[C] Ministry of Commerce and Industry[D] Ministry of Education"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of Health and Family Welfare]",
      "hint": "Notes:Union Health Ministry launched a learning management information system SAKSHAM-Stimulating Advanced Knowledge for Sustainable Health Management.\nHealthcare workers and administrators can utilise SAKSHAM to acquire globally relevant knowledge."
    },
    {
      "question": "34. ‘Big Ben’ is the famous clock located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] UK[C] Australia[D] France"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [UK]",
      "hint": "Notes:Big Ben is the nickname given to the Great Bell of the Great Clock of Westminster, United Kingdom. It had failed to bong on May 10, when the dials of the clock on top of the Elizabeth Tower briefly stopped.\nFor hundreds of years, it was called the Clock Tower, and was renamed Elizabeth Tower in 2012 to mark the Diamond Jubilee of Elizabeth II."
    },
    {
      "question": "35. The invasion of a tiny insect named ‘Eretmoptera murphyi’ is changing the ecosystem of which continent?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Australia[B] Antarctica[C] Asia[D] Africa"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Antarctica]",
      "hint": "Notes:Eretmoptera murphyi is a flightless midge. It is currently changing Antarctica’s Signy Island soil and ecosystem by feasting on dead organic matter.\nIt has led to faster plant decomposition, thus increasing the soil nitrate levels by three-five times compared to places on the island where the midge is absent."
    },
    {
      "question": "36. Who is the first Indian scientist to become the Fellow of the Royal Society this year?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Rajeev Varshney[B] Ranjit Kher[C] Rajendra Singh[D] Ratna Sagar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Rajeev Varshney]",
      "hint": "Notes:Rajeev Varshney is an Indian agricultural scientist known for his contribution towards decoding legumes’ genomes and developing new varieties of chickpeas.\nHe is the only new Indian scientist to become the Fellow of the Royal Society this year. Rajeev Varshney is fourth Indian agricultural scientist to become FRS."
    },
    {
      "question": "37. Which institution released the ‘World Tourism Barometer’ Report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UNICEF[B] UNWTO[C] UNDP[D] World Bank"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [UNWTO]",
      "hint": "Notes:World Tourism Organization is a specialized agency of the United Nations. According to the second UNWTO World Tourism Barometer of the year, international tourism is rebounding to pre-pandemic levels.\nAround 235 million tourists travelled internationally in the first three months of 2023. Overall, international arrivals reached 80% of pre-pandemic levels in the first quarter of 2023."
    },
    {
      "question": "38. Amy Pope, the first woman Director General of the International Organization for Migration, is from which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] United States[B] Germany[C] Australia[D] UK"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [United States]",
      "hint": "Notes:Amy Pope of the United States was recently elected as the direct general of the International Organization for Migration.\nShe is the first woman to take up this position in the organisation in its more than 70-year-old history. USA is the largest bilateral donor of the International Organization for Migration."
    },
    {
      "question": "39. Which institution released the ‘Spring 2023 Economic Forecast’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] World Bank[B] European Commission[C] WEF[D] IMF"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [European Commission]",
      "hint": "Notes:The ‘Spring 2023 Economic Forecast’ was released recently by the European Commission. It revised the 2023-24 growth outlook of 20 countries with the Euro as their currency to 1.1 percent from the previous estimate of 0.9 percent.\nAs per the report, lower energy prices, abating supply constraints and a strong labour market supported moderate growth in the first quarter of 2023."
    },
    {
      "question": "40. ‘AutoGrow Project’ is implemented by which institutions?",
      "options": [
        "[A] IIHR and IITB[B] IIHR and IITM[C] ICAR and IITB[D] ICAR and IITM"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [IIHR and IITB]",
      "hint": "Notes:AutoGrow Project is implemented jointly by the Indian Institute of Horticultural Research (IIHR) and Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IITB).\nUnder this project, an automated greenhouse system is developed for precision in agriculture.  The system has three configurations; hydroponics, open grow farming, and vertical setup."
    },
    {
      "question": "41. Dal Lake, which was seen in the news, is located in which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Assam[B] Jammu and Kashmir[C] Karnataka[D] Uttarakhand"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:Dal Lake is the second largest lake in Jammu and Kashmir. CRPF recently conducted a special drill in this lake as part of security preparedness ahead of the G20 summit in Kashmir.\nMarine Commandos (MORCOS) have also done similar security drills in Dal Lake. The G20 international summit in Kashmir was held from May 22 to May 24 at Sher-e-Kashmir International Conference Centre (SKICC) on the banks of Dal Lake."
    },
    {
      "question": "42. What is the sixth submarine of the first batch of six Kalvari-class submarines for the Indian Navy?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Virat[B] Varun[C] Vaghsheer[D] Vrindavan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Vaghsheer]",
      "hint": "Notes:The sixth submarine of the first batch of six Kalvari-class submarines for the Indian Navy under Project-75 is Vaghsheer.\nThe submarine is expected to be delivered to the Indian Navy in early 2024. The submarine was launched in 2022 by Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders Limited (MDL)."
    },
    {
      "question": "43. What is the name of the central programme launched to promote artificial intelligence in India and beyond?",
      "options": [
        "[A] BharatAI[B] INDIAai[C] BHIMai[D] VIKASai"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [INDIAai]",
      "hint": "Notes:INDIAai is a central programme launched to promote artificial intelligence in India and beyond.  The National AI Portal of India is a joint venture by MEITY, NEGD and NASSCOM.\nSeven working groups set up under INDIAai are expected to submit their recommendations for a comprehensive framework governing various facets of AI in the near future."
    },
    {
      "question": "44. Kambalakonda Wildlife Sanctuary is located in which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kerala[B] Karnataka[C] Andhra Pradesh[D] West Bengal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Andhra Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Kambalakonda Wildlife Sanctuary is located near Visakhapatnam, Andhra Pradesh. Barkudia limbless skink has been spotted recently at the Kambalakonda Wildlife Sanctuary.\nIt is a small reptile known for its unique limbless body and adaptation capability."
    },
    {
      "question": "45. Which state is set to build the ‘Maharana Pratap Lok’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Maharashtra[B] Madhya Pradesh[C] Assam[D] West Bengal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Madhya Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Maharana Pratap Lok will be built by the Madhya Pradesh government. The ‘Veer Shiromani Maharana Pratap Lok’ will be constructed in Bhopal.\nIt will be set up in memory of the Rajput King of Mewar Maharana Pratap. The Chief Minister also declared Maharana Pratap’s birth anniversary as holiday in the state."
    },
    {
      "question": "46. Which Article allows the President to promulgate the ordinance during recess of the Parliament?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Article 45[B] Article 123[C] Article 245[D] Article 301"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Article 123]",
      "hint": "Notes:Article 123 of the Indian Constitution allows the President to promulgate the ordinance during recess of the Parliament. The ordinance has the same force and effect as the Act of Parliament.\nPresident of India exercised legislative power under Article 123 of the Constitution, during the period Parliament was in recess, to promulgate The Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi (Amendment) Ordinance, 2023 (Ordinance)."
    },
    {
      "question": "47. Which super-computer was ranked at 75th position at Top 500 Global Supercomputing List?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ARJUN[B] AIRAWAT[C] ANANYA[D] AVIGHNA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [AIRAWAT]",
      "hint": "Notes:AIRAWAT is an AI supercomputer in the Centre for Development of Advanced Computing (C-DAC), Pune. It is India’s largest and fastest AI supercomputing system, with a remarkable speed of 13,170 teraflops.\nIt was ranked at 75th position in the world by the 61st edition of Top 500 Global Supercomputing List. The supercomputer has been installed this year."
    },
    {
      "question": "48. ‘Gerald R. Ford’ the largest aircraft carrier in the world, is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] Russia[C] France[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:USS Gerald R. Ford is the largest aircraft carrier in the world. It recently made its first foreign call.\nThe ship is named after the 38th President of the United States, Gerald Ford. The ship sailed into Oslo, a first for such a U.S. ship, in a show of NATO force at a time of heightened tension between NATO and Russia over the war in Ukraine."
    },
    {
      "question": "49. Tina Turner, which was seen in the news, was associated with which profession?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Author[B] Singer[C] Politician[D] Sports person"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Singer]",
      "hint": "Notes:Tina Turner, a famous American musician, recently passed away at the age of 83. She is the first African-American woman rock-and-roll artist.\nTurner announced her retirement in 2000, a year after releasing her final solo album, Twenty Four Seven. Her autobiography ‘My Love Story’ was released in 2018."
    },
    {
      "question": "50. El Popo Volcano, which was seen in the news, is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indonesia[B] Mexico[C] Japan[D] Philippines"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Mexico]",
      "hint": "Notes:Popocatepetl, commonly known as El Popo volcano, has recently started spewing plumes. It is situated in Mexico.\nPopocatepetl means “smoking mountain” in the Nahuatl language. After lying dormant for more than 70 years, it has been spewing toxic fumes, ash, and lumps of incandescent rock."
    }
  ],
  "type": "current-affairs-quiz-may-2023",
  "__v": 0
},
{
  "_id": {
    "$oid": "651556a24a8b33acb2b5b0d0"
  },
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "1. ‘Atal Bhujal Yojana’, which was seen in the news, is implemented by which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of MSME[B] Ministry of Jal Shakti[C] Ministry of Commerce and Industry[D] Ministry of Defence"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of Jal Shakti]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Atal Bhujal Yojana (Atal Jal), a central sector water conservation scheme, will continue for an additional two years beyond its original 2025 end date. It is implemented by the Ministry of Jal Shakti.\nThe major objective of the Scheme is to improve the management of groundwater resources in select water stressed areas in identified states viz. Gujarat, Haryana, Karnataka, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. Which institution released the ‘Forever Toxic: The science on health threats from plastic recycling’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] WMO[B] UNEP[C] WHO[D] Greenpeace Philippines"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Greenpeace Philippines]",
      "hint": "Notes:The report titled “Forever Toxic: The science on health threats from plastic recycling” was released recently by Greenpeace Philippines. According to this report, recycling can increase the toxicity of plastics.\nThe report was released ahead of the second session of the Intergovernmental Negotiating Committee to develop a Global Plastics Treaty, being held at Paris, France."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Which institutions released the ‘Hunger Hotspots –Early warnings on acute food insecurity’ report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] World Bank- IMF[B] IMF- WEF[C] FAO- WFP[D] WHO- FAO"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [FAO- WFP]",
      "hint": "Notes:A new report titled “Hunger Hotspots – FAO-WFP early warnings on acute food insecurity” was released recently.\nAccording to this report, Pakistan, Afghanistan and Myanmar are among the hunger hotspots in the world. Acute food insecurity can potentially increase in magnitude and severity for 18 areas in 22 countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Which country has launched USD 17 billion project known as the ‘Route of Development’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Iraq[B] Iran[C] UAE[D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Iraq]",
      "hint": "Notes:Iraq presented an ambitious plan to turn itself into a regional transportation hub by developing its road and rail infrastructure, linking Europe with the Middle East.\nOnce completed, the $17 billion project known as the ‘Route of Development’ would span the length of the country, stretching 1,200 km  from the northern border with Turkiye to the Gulf in the south."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. Which institution released guidelines for Investor Protection Fund (IPF) and Investor Services Fund (ISF)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] RBI[B] SEBI[C] PFRDA[D] NITI Aayog"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [SEBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:Capital Market Regulator SEBI- the Securities Exchange Board of India has released guidelines for Investor Protection Fund (IPF) and Investor Services Fund (ISF).\nThese funds are maintained by stock exchanges and depositories. The new changes aim to strengthen investor protection measures and promote financial literacy and participation in the securities market."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which institution launched ‘e-Appeal scheme 2023’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] CBDT[B] CBIC[C] RBI[D] SEBI"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [CBDT]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Central Board of Direct Taxes (CBDT) recently launched “e appeal” scheme announced in the budget.\nIts aim is to minimize pendency of appeals related to Tax Deducted at Source (TDS) default issues and tax collection at source (TCS). The scheme empowers the Joint Commissioner (Appeals) for disposing of appeals filed before it or allocated or transferred to it."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Which city is the host of the ‘International Organic Mahotsav-2023’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Mysuru[B] Guwahati[C] Visakhapatnam[D] Kochi"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Visakhapatnam]",
      "hint": "Notes:International Organic Mahotsav-2023 is being organized from June 2 to 4 in Gadiraju Palace in Visakhapatnam.\nThe Rythu Sadhikara Samstha (RySS) is organising the event, which will connect farmers practicing natural farming methods and potential consumers of these crops."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. As of 2023, India has how many joint logistics nodes?",
      "options": [
        "[A] One[B] Three[C] Five[D] Seven"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Three]",
      "hint": "Notes:The armed forces are planning to set up additional joint logistics nodes across the country to boost integration in their logistical needs and streamline their supply chains.\nWhile the last joint logistics node was operationalised in Mumbai in April 2021, the nodes in Guwahati and Tri-Services, Port Blair were operationalised in January 2021. The Joint Operations Division under the Headquarters Integrated Defence Staff has been responsible for establishing the nodes."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Which institution accepted the ‘Draft Resolution on the Impact of Chemicals, Waste and Pollution on Human Health’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] WHO[B] World Bank[C] WEF[D] IMF"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [WHO]",
      "hint": "Notes:The WHO member countries have recently accepted a draft resolution on the impact of chemicals, waste and pollution on human health during the 76th WHA.\nIt urged the healthcare sector to develop a regulatory framework, national human bio-monitoring and surveillance programmes to track chemicals that impact human health."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. Which country leads the ‘Combined Maritime Forces’ coalition?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Russia[B] USA[C] UK[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Combined Maritime Forces is a US-led maritime coalition involved in securing tense Gulf waterways. The UAE recently withdrew from this coalition.\nThe coalition is tasked with securing tense Gulf waterways that are vital to the global oil trade. The coalition had 38 member states."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. Which institution submitted its report on the sedition law to the law ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Election Commission[B] Law Commission[C] Central Vigilance Commission[D] Central Bureau of Investigation"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Law Commission]",
      "hint": "Notes:The 22nd Law Commission submitted its report on the sedition law to the law ministry, providing its recommendations on amending section 124A of the Indian Penal Code.\nEarlier, the 21st Law Commission in August 2018 had published a consultation paper seeking public views on the sedition law."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. Which country has approved ‘Debt Ceiling Deal’ to raise the government’s borrowing limit?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Sri Lanka[C] USA[D] Afghanistan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:The US Congress has approved the debt ceiling deal to raise the government’s borrowing limit and thwarting a potentially catastrophic default on US debt repayments.\nIt will allow the federal government to borrow money until after the next presidential election in November 2024. The agreement keeps non-defence spending flat next year, with a 1% rise in 2025."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. Which country unveiled the ‘Obstetric Fistula Strategic Plan’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Zambia[C] Malaysia[D] Japan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Zambia]",
      "hint": "Notes:Obstetric fistula is a health condition characterized by the formation of an opening between the passage through which a baby is delivered and the urinary or digestive system.\nZamibia recently unveiled the Obstetric Fistula Strategic Plan for the period 2022 to 2026. On May 23, Zambia commemorated International Day for Elimination of Obstetric Fistula with theme “20 years on — progress but not enough! Act Now to End Fistula by 2030”. As of 2018, more than 33,000 women and girls were affected in the country."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. The United States signed a trade deal with which country, and was warned by China?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Taiwan[B] Ukraine[C] India[D] Sri Lanka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Taiwan]",
      "hint": "Notes:The United States and Taiwan have signed a trade deal aimed at deepening economic relations between both sides in a move that has sparked a warning from China.\nWashington and Taipei maintain a multibillion-dollar annual trade and unofficial ties through the de facto US embassy. The Chinese foreign ministry accused Washington of violating agreements on the status of Taiwan."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. Which neighbouring country recorded an annual inflation rate of 37.97% in May 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Pakistan[B] Afghanistan[C] Nepal[D] Myanmar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Pakistan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Pakistan’s annual inflation rate rose to 37.97% in May, the statistics bureau said, adding to its problems of a balance of payment crisis and the risk of a sovereign default.\nIn April, the bureau said Pakistan’s CPI at 36.5% was the highest recorded, and this is the national record for the second month in a row."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Which city is the headquarters of Pharmaceutical Inspection Convention and Pharmaceutical Inspection Co-operation Scheme (PIC/S)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] New York[B] Geneva[C] Rome[D] Paris"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Geneva]",
      "hint": "Notes:India is planning to join the Pharmaceutical Inspection Convention and Pharmaceutical Inspection Co-operation Scheme (PIC/S). It is headquartered in Geneva, Switzerland.\nIt is an global regime that promotes cooperation between countries and regulatory authorities in good manufacturing practices (GMP) in order to improve the quality of their medical products."
    },
    {
      "question": "17. Strawberry Moon is the full moon of which month?",
      "options": [
        "[A] June[B] July[C] August[D] September"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [June]",
      "hint": "Notes:June’s full moon, also known as the Strawberry Moon, rose on June 3. The moon will then reach new moon on June 18, at which point it will be totally lost in the sun’s glare.\nThe next full moon, July’s Buck Moon, will rise on Monday, July 3."
    },
    {
      "question": "18. What is the name of the portal launched for monitoring the implementation of Centrally Sponsored Schemes of Justice Ministry ?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Nyaya Vikas Portal[B] Info Vikas Portal[C] CSS Monitor Portal[D] Bharat Scheme Portal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Nyaya Vikas Portal]",
      "hint": "Notes:Nyaya Vikas Portal was launched recently for monitoring the implementation of Centrally Sponsored Schemes.\nIt provides information regarding the funding, documentation, project monitoring and approval of these schemes. The Department of Justice has been implementing the Centrally Sponsored Scheme (CSS) for Development of Infrastructure Facilities for Districts and Subordinate Judiciary since 1993-94."
    },
    {
      "question": "19. What is Sea Ice?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Frozen CO2[B] Frozen sea water[C] Frozen salt[D] Frozen sugar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Frozen sea water]",
      "hint": "Notes:Sea ice is frozen seawater which floats on the ocean surface. It undergoes a melting process during summer and then re-freezes during the winter season. It forms in both the Arctic and the Antarctic in each hemisphere’s winter.\nA new study revealed that Arctic may become sea ice-free in the summers by 2030s."
    },
    {
      "question": "20. ‘Prerna: The Vernacular School’, which was seen in the news, is located in which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Gujarat[B] Bihar[C] Odisha[D] Telangana"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Gujarat]",
      "hint": "Notes:Prime Minister Narendra Modi’s first school in Gujarat’s Mehsana district is being developed as a model school called “Prerna” to inspire youth of the country.\nIn this school, two children from each district in India will be enrolled to spend around a week in the school and they will be trained on how to live a evolved life."
    },
    {
      "question": "21. As per the ‘World Bank’s Latest Global Economic Prospects Report’, what is the growth rate of the global economy in 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 2.1%[B] 2.5%[C] 2.7%[D] 3.0%"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [2.1%]",
      "hint": "Notes:The World Bank’s most recent Global Economic Prospects report predicts that the global economy will experience a growth rate of 2.1% in 2023, compared to 3.1% in 2022.\nThe report also highlights that trade in 2023 is expected to expand at a significantly slower pace, less than one-third of its pre-pandemic levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "22. Which state commissioned the K-FON Fibre Optic Network Project?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Karnataka[B] Kerala[C] Assam[D] Telangana"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Kerala]",
      "hint": "Notes:Kerala Chief Minister Pinarayi Vijayan commissioned the first phase of the Kerala Fibre Optic Network (K-FON).\nThe project is aimed at providing free Internet access to 20 lakh below poverty line (BPL) families and connecting 30,000 government institutions, as well as providing Internet connection at nominal rate to the public."
    },
    {
      "question": "23. Which Armed Force procured the first barge, LSAM 15 (Yard 125) from a Thane-based private company?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indian Army[B] Indian Navy[C] Indian Air Force[D] Indian Coast Guard"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Indian Navy]",
      "hint": "Notes:The first Ammunition Cum Torpedo Cum Missile (ACTCM) barge, LSAM 15 (Yard 125), has been delivered to the Indian Navy recently by the Suryadipta Projects, Thane.\nThis is in line with the “Aatmanirbhar Bharat” initiatives of the Indian government."
    },
    {
      "question": "24. ‘Espionage Act’ is associated with which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] Russia[C] Ukraine[D] China"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Espionage Act is a US legislation that was enacted after the First World War to criminalize certain conducts associated with the mishandling of sensitive government records concerning to the national defense.\nFormer US President Donald Trump has recently become the most high-profile individual to ever face criminal charges under this Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "25. Janan Bushehri, is the only woman legislator elected in which country’s general election?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Israel[B] Kuwait[C] UAE[D] Iran"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Kuwait]",
      "hint": "Notes:Opposition lawmakers won a majority in Kuwait’s parliament with only one woman -Janan Bushehri elected, after the Gulf state’s seventh general election in just over a decade.\nSince Kuwait adopted a parliamentary system in 1962, the legislature has been dissolved around a dozen times."
    },
    {
      "question": "26. Which country is the host of this year’s edition of ‘Miss World pageant’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Sri Lanka[B] India[C] Australia[D] USA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:Miss World pageant is one of the oldest beauty pageants in the world. The Miss World Organization recently announced that India is the venue for this year’s edition of the event.\nContestants from over 130 countries will showcase their talents, intelligence, and compassion. They will participate in a series of rigorous competitions, including talent showcases, sports challenges, and charitable initiatives etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "27. ADB signed a loan agreement with India for implementing ‘Subtropical Horticulture, Irrigation, and Value Addition Project’ in which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Assam[B] Gujarat[C] Himachal Pradesh[D] West Bengal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Himachal Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:A USD 130 million loan agreement was signed recently between the Asian Development Bank (ADB) and the Indian Government.\nThe agreement is for the implementation of the Himachal Pradesh Subtropical Horticulture, Irrigation, and Value Addition Project. Its aim is to promote horticulture in the state."
    },
    {
      "question": "28. Which state is the host of the ‘SAI20 Summit’ in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Assam[B] Kerala[C] Goa[D] Odisha"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Goa]",
      "hint": "Notes:Supreme Audit Institutions (SAI) 20 Summit under India’s G20 Presidency commenced recently in Goa.\nThe Summit has called upon the Supreme Audit Institutions (SAI) to take measures for suitable integration of artificial intelligence (AI) in audit processes and tasks for improved audit efficiency and effectiveness."
    },
    {
      "question": "29. A celt, belonging to the neolithic period, was recently discovered in which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kerala[B] Karnataka[C] Tamil Nadu[D] Andhra Pradesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:A celt, belonging to the neolithic period, was recently discovered in Poothinatham village in Dharmapuri, Tamil Nadu.\nArchaeological excavations are being carried out by Tamil Nadu’s Department of Archaeology in the village. It was a significant discovery as the celt was used as either a plough or an axe, and was made of Doloraid stone."
    },
    {
      "question": "30. Which city hosted the first National Training Conclave?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kolkata[B] New Delhi[C] Pune[D] Mysuru"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [New Delhi]",
      "hint": "Notes:Prime Minister Narendra Modi recently inaugurated the first National Training Conclave in New Delhi.\nIt is an effort by the government aiming to strengthen training infrastructure for civil servants across India. The event was hosted by the Capacity Building Commission (CBC) and is sponsored by the National Programme for Civil Services Capacity Building (NPCSCB) – ‘Mission Karmayogi’."
    },
    {
      "question": "31. What is the outlay for 3 schemes related to disaster management, which were announced by the Government of India, recently?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Rs.1000 crore[B] Rs.2000 crore[C] Rs.8000 crore[D] Rs.9000 crore"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Rs.8000 crore]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Union Home Minister, has recently announced three schemes worth ₹8,000 crore related to disaster management, which includes modernisation of fire services, flood mitigation in seven major cities and prevention of landslides in 17 states.\nIt was informed by the Minister, that for modernization and expansion of fire brigade services, about ₹5,000 crore assistance will be given to all States and  to mitigate the danger of floods in urban areas, in seven major cities, ₹2,500 crore will be given."
    },
    {
      "question": "32. Which country has decided to rejoin UNESCO?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] USA[C] Ukraine[D] Russia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:The United States plans to rejoin the U.N. cultural and scientific agency UNESCO and pay more than USD 600 million in back dues.\nThe officials of U.S. have stated that the country’s decision to return was motivated by concern that China is filling the gap left by the U.S. in UNESCO policymaking, notably in setting standards for artificial intelligence and technology education around the world."
    },
    {
      "question": "33. Which country returned remains of Indigenous Maori and Moriori people to New Zealand?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] UK[C] Germany[D] France"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Germany]",
      "hint": "Notes:The remains of 95 Indigenous New Zealanders as well as artefacts and cultural treasures have been returned to New Zealand from museums and universities in Germany.\nThe ancestral remains of the 95 Maori and Moriori individuals, including six toi moko – Maori mummified tattooed heads – were welcomed to Te Papa, New Zealand’s national museum."
    },
    {
      "question": "34. Where is the 2025 IIAS (International Institute of Administrative Sciences) annual conference proposed to be held?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kochi[B] New Delhi[C] Mussoorie[D] Hyderabad"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Kochi]",
      "hint": "Notes:The 2025 IIAS (International Institute of Administrative Sciences) annual conference is proposed to be held in India, at Kochi. The event will be attended by 30 member countries, 18 national sections and over 50 academic institutions.\nThe International Institute of Administrative Sciences, which is headquartered in Brussels, Belgium, is a federation of member states, national sections and research institutions which elaborate on pubic administration solutions."
    },
    {
      "question": "35. What is the new name of the ‘Nehru Memorial Museum and Library Society’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India Memorial Museum and Library Society[B] Prime Ministers’ Museum and Library Society[C] Swatantra Memorial Museum and Library Society[D] Bharat Memorial Museum and Library Society"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Prime Ministers’ Museum and Library Society]",
      "hint": "Notes:During a special meeting of the Nehru Memorial Museum and Library Society, a decision was made to modify its name to the Prime Ministers’ Museum and Library Society.\nThe meeting was chaired by Rajnath Singh, the Union Defence Minister and Vice-President of the Society."
    },
    {
      "question": "36. ‘Fish kill’ phenomenon was recently recorded in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Thailand[C] USA[D] Japan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:‘Fish kill’ refers to the abrupt and unforeseen demise of numerous fish or other aquatic creatures within a limited timeframe, predominantly concentrated in a specific area.\nIt was recorded recently in Texas. Among the dead fish in the shores, most were menhaden but there were also some sharks, trout, bass, catfish and stingrays."
    },
    {
      "question": "37. Which institution issued Guidelines on Product Offerings by online bond platform providers (OBPP)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] RBI[B] SEBI[C] NPCI[D] IRDAI"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [SEBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) has imposed restrictions on online bond platform providers, prohibiting them from offering products other than listed debt securities.\nHowever, SEBI has allowed these platforms to offer specific securities such as Government Securities, Treasury Bills, listed Sovereign Gold Bonds, listed municipal debt securities, and listed securitized debt instruments."
    },
    {
      "question": "38. Which country has won the title of ‘World Squash Championship’ in 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Egypt[C] China[D] Japan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Egypt]",
      "hint": "Notes:Egypt has retained World Squash Championship, after beating Malaysia 2-1 in the final in Chennai.\nThe third place was shared jointly by hosts India and Japan. India was beaten by Malaysia 3-0 in the semi-final. Eight countries took part in the World Squash Championship."
    },
    {
      "question": "39. Which Asian country approved a bill with the objective for awareness and acceptance of the LGBT community?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Japan[C] South Korea[D] Nepal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Japan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Japan recently approved a bill with the objective of fostering awareness and acceptance of the LGBT community. However, concerns have been raised regarding the absence of human rights safeguards in the legislation and the possibility of reinforcing specific forms of discrimination."
    },
    {
      "question": "40. Which country is the host of the ‘Ex Khaan Quest 2023’ multilateral peacekeeping joint exercise?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Sri Lanka[C] Mongolia[D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Mongolia]",
      "hint": "Notes:Ex Khaan Quest 2023 is a multilateral peacekeeping joint exercise that is currently being held in Mongolia. It involved the participation of military contingents and observers from around 20 countries.\nPresident of Mongolia inaugurated the Exercise, which is co-sponsored by Mongolian Armed Forces (MAF) and United States Army Pacific Command (USARPAC)."
    },
    {
      "question": "41. What is the expansion of ‘NIXI’, which celebrated its 20th foundation day recently?",
      "options": [
        "[A] National Internet Exchange of India[B] National Information Exchange of India[C] National iOS Exchange of India[D] National Interactive Exchange of India"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [National Internet Exchange of India]",
      "hint": "Notes:National Internet Exchange of India (NIXI) celebrated its 20th foundation day on 19th June this year. NIXI has made remarkable efforts to establish a strong and all-encompassing digital environment in the nation through its various business divisions, which include Internet Exchange, .IN Registry, IRINN, and NIXI-CSC Data Services Ltd."
    },
    {
      "question": "42. What is the name of the plant which grows on another plant/tree drawing moisture and nutrients not from host?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Parasite[B] Epiphyte[C] Phorophyte[D] Photophyte"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Epiphyte]",
      "hint": "Notes:Epiphytes grow on another plant/tree merely for physical support, drawing moisture and nutrients from the air, rain, water or from debris accumulating around it, and not from the host.\nThe survival of epiphytic orchids in the Dooars and Darjeeling hills are threatened due to deforestation. They are known for their medicinal properties."
    },
    {
      "question": "43. The Child Helpline 1098 is set to be consolidated with which helpline?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 100[B] 101[C] 112[D] 1091"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [112]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Ministry of Women and Child Development had announced the consolidation of the existing child helpline (1098), operated by Childline, with the women’s helpline and Emergency Response Support System (112), as part of its “One Nation, One Helpline” initiative.\nAndhra Pradesh, Arunachal Pradesh, Ladakh, Puducherry, Goa, Dadra and Nagar Haveli and Daman and Diu, Mizoram, Gujarat, and Bihar are set to launch the integrated child helpline service by the end of this month, making it the first of its kind in India."
    },
    {
      "question": "44. Which Union Ministry organized the ‘Ocean Ring of Yoga’ special event?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Defence[B] Ministry of AYUSH[C] Ministry of External Affairs[D] Ministry of Sports"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of AYUSH]",
      "hint": "Notes:To commemorate the International Yoga Day 2023, the Ministry of AYUSH has organized a special event called the ‘Ocean Ring of Yoga’ to symbolize unity and solidarity.\nAs part of this initiative, Indian Navy ships stationed in the Indian Ocean Region are visiting different ports of friendly foreign nations to promote the message of ‘Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam,’ which is also the theme for IDY 23."
    },
    {
      "question": "45. In the recently released ‘Motor Third Party Premium and Liability Rules’, by what percent the premium for third-party motor insurance is increased?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 2%[B] 2.5%[C] 5%[D] No change"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [No change]",
      "hint": "Notes:In the recently released Motor Third Party Premium and Liability Rules (FY) 2023-24 by the Ministry of Road Transport and Highways in consultation with IRDAI, no change is proposed in the premium rates for third-party motor insurance for FY2023-24.\nThe Government of India has made it mandatory in India for motor vehicles to get a third-party insurance policy under the provisions of Motor Vehicles Act of India, 1988."
    },
    {
      "question": "46. What is the name of the 21-foot submersible which disappeared recently?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Saturn[B] Jupiter[C] Titan[D] Max"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Titan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Titan is a 21-foot submersible that disappeared recently. It is operated by OceanGate Expeditions, an undersea exploration company that has been making yearly voyages to the Titanic since 2021.\nAs per the authorities, the submersible suffered a “catastrophic implosion,” killing all five people on board while descending to explore the wreckage of the famous ship."
    },
    {
      "question": "47. Which concept states that black holes are not completely black but emit a form of radiation over time?",
      "options": [
        "[A] CV Raman radiation[B] Hawking radiation[C] Newton radiation[D] Einstein radiation"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Hawking radiation]",
      "hint": "Notes:Hawking radiation is a theoretical concept in physics proposed by the renowned physicist Stephen\nHawking. It suggests that black holes are not completely black but emit a form of radiation over time. Chinese researchers have utilized quantum computing to simulate black hole physics and test Stephen Hawking’s theory on Hawking radiaation."
    },
    {
      "question": "48. Joha rice, which was seen in the news, is from which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] West Bengal[B] Assam[C] Odisha[D] Bihar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Assam]",
      "hint": "Notes:Scientists at the Institute of Advanced Study in Science and Technology conducted research on the nutraceutical properties of Joha rice, an aromatic rice grown in the Northeastern region of India, especially Assam.\nThey found that Joha rice is effective in reducing blood glucose levels and preventing the onset of diabetes, making it a promising choice for managing diabetes."
    },
    {
      "question": "49. ‘Al-Hakim bi-Amr Allah mosque’ is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Israel[B] UAE[C] Iran[D] Egypt"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Egypt]",
      "hint": "Notes:Prime Minister Narendra Modi is scheduled to tour the Al-Hakim bi-Amr Allah mosque, situated in Cairo, Egypt. It is named after Al-Hakim bi-Amr Allah (985-1021), the 16th Fatimid Caliph.\nAs the fourth oldest mosque in Egypt and the second largest, it holds significant historical and architectural importance."
    },
    {
      "question": "50. ‘Blue Pansy (Junonia Orithya)’ has been named as the official butterfly of which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Karnataka[B] Jammu and Kashmir[C] Arunachal Pradesh[D] Sikkim"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:Blue Pansy (Junonia Orithya) has been named the official butterfly of Jammu and Kashmir. The Blue Pansy, a type of vivid blue butterfly, can be observed in different regions of Southeast Asia, Australia, and Africa.\nThese butterflies, recognized for their territorial behavior, display 26 distinct local subspecies within their habitat."
    }
  ],
  "type": "current-affairs-quiz-june-2023",
  "__v": 0
},
{
  "_id": {
    "$oid": "651556a34a8b33acb2b5b0d2"
  },
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "1. Which bloc has conducted a joint military drill named ‘Solidarity Exercise’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] EU[B] G-20[C] ASEAN[D] BIMSTEC"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [ASEAN]",
      "hint": "Notes:‘Solidarity exercise’ is a joint military drill involving the ASEAN nations -Indonesia, Vietnam, Malaysia, Brunei and the Philippines.\nThis year, Indonesia holds the rotating chair of the regional bloc. The military exercise has been planned amid the tensions with China."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. Honeybee hives in which country faced the second highest mortality rate ever recorded?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] USA[C] Australia[D] Indonesia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:According to a recent survey by the University of Maryland and Auburn University, honeybee hives in the US faced the second highest mortality rate ever recorded, with beekeepers losing almost half of their managed colonies.\nHowever, the survey also revealed that the total number of honeybee colonies in the country has remained relatively steady, despite this significant loss."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Which company introduced ‘Perspectives’ tab feature, which allows users to explore diverse viewpoints on a particular topic?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Google[B] Microsoft[C] Apple[D] Samsung"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Google]",
      "hint": "Notes:Google, owned by Alphabet, introduced the ‘Perspectives’ tab feature, which allows users to explore diverse viewpoints on a particular topic. By selecting the filter, users can access a range of content such as videos from platforms like TikTok and YouTube, written posts from discussion boards and social media, and more, as explained in a blog post by Google."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Which company is set to buy the Danske Bank’s IT centre in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] HDFC Bank[B] Infosys[C] Axis Bank[D] Tata Consultancy Services"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Infosys]",
      "hint": "Notes:Infosys has announced a long-term collaboration with Danske Bank. The projected agreement worth USD 454 million for a 5-year term has the possibility to renew for an extra year up to three times.\nAs part of this agreement, Infosys will also buy Danske Bank’s IT centre in India, which employs over 1,400 people. Danske Bank, headquartered in Denmark, provides banking services to individuals and businesses, as well as large corporations and institutions."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. Which institution leads the ‘Trans-Asia Railway (TAR) network’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] World Bank[B] UN[C] WEF[D] IMF"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [UN]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Asian Development Bank (ADB) is set to provide 400 million US dollars in loans to Bangladesh for the construction of 102 kilometers long dual gauge railways between Chattogram and Cox’s Bazar to promote trade, investment and tourism.\nChattogram-Cox’s Bazar Railway is part of the Trans-Asia Railway (TAR) network, an initiative led by the United Nations, aiming to provide seamless rail links between Asia and Europe to better connect people and markets."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which state/UT hosted the ‘Vitasta’ program to spread its art culture and literature?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Odisha[B] West Bengal[C] Jammu and Kashmir[D] Jharkhand"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Jammu and Kashmir]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Vitasta program was conducted with the aim of spreading the diverse art, culture, literature, craft, and cuisine of Kashmir to every corner of the country.\nThis series of events, which commenced in Chennai and concluded in Srinagar, witnessed a remarkable level of interest among the youth in understanding and embracing the vibrant Kashmiri culture."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Which country has been removed from UNGA Security Council Children and Armed Conflict Report?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indonesia[B] India[C] Sri Lanka[D] Afghanistan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:Since 2010, India has been included in the report of the Secretary-General on Children and armed conflict, alongside other countries such as Burkina Faso, Cameroon, the Lake Chad basin, Nigeria, Pakistan, and the Philippines.\nAs a result of the government’s efforts to enhance the protection of children, India is presently not mentioned in the United Nations General Assembly Security Council Children and Armed Conflict Report of the Secretary-General."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Which state/UT is associated with ‘EKAMRA project’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] West Bengal[B] Odisha[C] Bihar[D] Gujarat"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Odisha]",
      "hint": "Notes:Odisha Chief Minister Naveen Patnaik initiated the Rs 280-crore EKAMRA project, aimed at enhancing the surroundings of the 11th-century Lingaraj Temple in Bhubaneswar, as part of his government’s commitment to the development of ancient temples.\nLaunched in 2019, the EKAMRA plan focuses on revitalizing approximately 80 acres of land surrounding the historic Lord Shiva shrine in the Ekamra Kshetra (ancient name of Bhubaneswar)."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Bald eagle is endemic to which part of the world?",
      "options": [
        "[A] North America[B] Africa[C] Ireland[D] Australia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [North America]",
      "hint": "Notes:The bald eagle is a bird of prey and a sea eagle found in North America. It is the national bird of USA. In 2007, the American bald eagle was taken off the endangered species list in the United States. Since then, there has been a consistent increase in the population of these birds.\nAccording to a report by the US Fish and Wildlife Service in 2021, the number of bald eagles in their natural habitat has multiplied by four since 2009."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. When is the International Day of Parliamentarism observed by the United Nations?",
      "options": [
        "[A] June 30[B] July 1[C] July 5[D] July 10"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [June 30]",
      "hint": "Notes:June 30 marks the annual celebration of the International Day of Parliamentarism which commemorates the founding of the Inter-Parliamentary Union (IPU) in 1889.\nThis special day was established by a United Nations General Assembly Resolution in 2018 to reflect on the progress made by parliaments worldwide in achieving predetermined goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. Which Indian Institution is working on the development of a secure signaling system for the Indian Railways, by using block chain technology?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ISRO[B] DRDO[C] IIT Kharagpur[D] Indian Army"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [IIT Kharagpur]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Indian Institute of Technology – Kharagpur, is working on the development of a secure signaling system for the Indian Railways, utilizing blockchain technology.\nThis tamper-proof system will incorporate advanced safety features and serve as a complement to the existing Data Logger, commonly known as the ‘Black Box,’ used in rolling stock."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. Which Union Ministry launched the ‘eSARAS mobile App’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Rural Development[B] Ministry of MSME[C] Ministry of Power[D] Ministry of External Affairs"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Rural Development]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Deendayal Antyodaya Yojna- National Rural Livelihoods Mission (DAY-NRLM) has introduced the eSARAS mobile App, aimed at enhancing marketing assistance for products created by women belonging to Self-help Groups (SHGs).\nThis app will contribute to the existing eCommerce endeavors focused on promoting SHG-produced goods. DAY-NRLM is a flagship scheme of Ministry of Rural Development."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. Which institution released the ‘Global research agenda for Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR) in human health?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UNEP[B] WHO[C] FAO[D] NITI Aayog"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [WHO]",
      "hint": "Notes:The ‘Quadripartite’ — comprising the United Nations (UN) Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), the UN Environment Programme (UNEP), the World Health Organization (WHO) and the World Organisation for Animal Health (WOAH) — released the One Health Priority Research Agenda on Antimicrobial Resistance through a webinar.\nThe organisations work specifically in the areas of human, animal, plant, and environmental health. WHO also launched a global research agenda for AMR in human health recently."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Ulez, which was seen in the news, is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indonesia[B] UK[C] USA[D] Australia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [UK]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Ulez, located in London, is a designated zone that mandates vehicles emitting significant amounts of pollutants to pay a charge upon entry.\nRecently, the expansion of the Ulez in London has led to a legal battle in the high court for the London Mayor."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The early universe experienced time passing at a rate one-fifth of the current rate, due to which phenomenon?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Time dilation[B] Time repression[C] Time solution[D] Time sedation"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Time dilation]",
      "hint": "Notes:According to a recent study, the early universe experienced time passing at a rate approximately one-fifth of the current rate, attributed to time dilation.\nThis conclusion was reached by scientists who studied a group of powerful black holes known as quasars."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Which institution released the ‘World Investment Report 2023’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UNCTAD[B] UNDP[C] FAO[D] UNEP"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [UNCTAD]",
      "hint": "Notes:According to the World Investment Report 2023 by the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD), the total amount of foreign direct investment (FDI) in developing Asian countries stayed at USD 662 billion in 2022.\nThis shows no significant change compared to the previous year. This figure, although representing approximately half of the worldwide inflows, remained constant."
    },
    {
      "question": "17. Which Union Ministry launched the ‘Scheme for Expansion and Modernization of Fire Services in the States’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Home Affairs[B] Ministry of Defence[C] Ministry of Youth Affairs and Sports[D] Ministry of Family and Health Affairs"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Home Affairs]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Ministry of Home Affairs has initiated the “Scheme for Expansion and Modernization of Fire Services in the States” with a total budget of Rs. 5,000 Crore.\nA sum of Rs. 500 crore from the overall budget has been allocated to incentivize States based on their implementation of legal and infrastructure-related reforms."
    },
    {
      "question": "18. The decrease in yields of Tomato recently in India is attributed to which of the following?",
      "options": [
        "[A] EL Nino[B] Tomato mosaic virus[C] Land mining in western Ghats[D] Loss of soil fertility"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Tomato mosaic virus]",
      "hint": "Notes:Tomato mosaic virus (ToMV) is a plant pathogenic virus. It is found worldwide and affects tomatoes and many other plants. Tomato growers in Maharashtra and Karnataka have attributed the decrease in yields to the tomato mosaic virus (ToMV) .\nToMV is a member of the Virgaviridae family and shares a close relationship with the tobacco mosaic virus (TMV)."
    },
    {
      "question": "19. Taylor Glacier is located in which region?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Australia[B] Greenland[C] Serbia[D] Antarctica"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Antarctica]",
      "hint": "Notes:After over a hundred years, scientists have finally determined the cause behind the crimson-colored discharge known as Blood Falls from Taylor Glacier in Antarctica.\nThrough analyzing samples collected in 2006 and 2018, researchers discovered that the presence of iron-rich nanospheres is responsible for the striking red coloration."
    },
    {
      "question": "20. Which institution released a consultation paper on Consolidated Cyber Security and Cyber Resilience Framework (CSCRF)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] NITI Aayog[B] SEBI[C] RBI[D] NASSCOM"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [SEBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:SEBI has recently released a consultation paper on ‘Consolidated Cyber Security and Cyber Resilience Framework (CSCRF) for Sebi Regulated Entities’.\nThis proposed framework requires all regulated entities to establish an updated cyber crisis management plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "21. What is Candida auris, which was seen in the news?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Fungus[B] Algae[C] Bacteria[D] Bird"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Fungus]",
      "hint": "Notes:Isolated live cultures of Candida auris, a new fungus that poses a significant worldwide health risk and is highly resistant to most antifungal treatments, have been found and documented within the ear canals of stray dogs receiving hospital care in Delhi.\nCandida auris is a multidrug-resistant oval-shaped fungus that is on the rise and has the potential to cause life-threatening outbreaks, particularly within healthcare facilities."
    },
    {
      "question": "22. Which Indian company has collaborated with Spain’s Navantia for Indian Navy’s P75 (I) Submarine Program Bid?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Larsen and Toubro[B] HAL[C] DRDO[D] BHEL"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Larsen and Toubro]",
      "hint": "Notes:Recently, Navantia from Spain and Larsen & Toubro joined forces by signing a collaborative agreement called the Teaming Agreement (TA), aiming to present a cutting-edge techno-commercial proposal for India’s esteemed P75 (India) submarine program.\nTo fulfill the requirements of Project 75 (I), the Indian bidder must establish a partnership with a Foreign Collaborator (FC) and successfully carry out the program’s implementation, delivering six conventional submarines equipped with Air-Independent Propulsion (AIP)."
    },
    {
      "question": "23. Louvre Museum, which was seen in the news, is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Russia[B] Ukraine[C] France[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [France]",
      "hint": "Notes:India is in the final stages of establishing a unique partnership with the renowned Louvre Museum to assist in the design and planning of the proposed new National Museum in the national capital, located on Raisina Hill.\nDuring Prime Minister Narendra Modi’s visit to Paris, an extensive cultural agreement is expected to be signed between the Indian and French governments."
    },
    {
      "question": "24. Which country hosted the ‘India-Arab business partnership conference’ recently?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Bahrain[C] UAE[D] Saudi Arabia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The sixth India-Arab Partnership Conference 2023 was organized in New Delhi. UAE was the third-largest trading partner of India while Saudi Arabia, was the fourth-largest partner during the last financial year.\nThe Conference has provided a useful platform to the business community on both sides to explore new prospects for trade and investment."
    },
    {
      "question": "25. P. indicus, which was seen in the news, belongs to which species?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Snake[B] Turtle[C] Shrimp[D] Dolphin"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Shrimp]",
      "hint": "Notes:Aquaculture scientists in India have successfully decoded the genome of an indigenous white shrimp variety called P. indicus.\nThis development is expected to enhance self-sufficiency and increase export earnings. The country currently relies on imported Pacific white shrimp, but this breakthrough aims to reduce dependence on a single species and promote the use of indigenous species for the benefit of the shrimp industry and farmers."
    },
    {
      "question": "26. Which state/UT approved a proposal to start Teacher Interface for Excellence (TIE) programme?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Uttar Pradesh[B] Rajasthan[C] West Bengal[D] Assam"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Rajasthan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Rajasthan Chief Minister Ashok Gehlot has approved a proposal for starting the Teacher Interface for Excellence (TIE) programme.\nUnder this, teachers of government universities, colleges and polytechnic colleges will get training in prestigious institutions of the country and abroad. A target has been set to train 500 teachers from across the State this year. The State government will spend ₹23.50 crore on research and training facilities for teachers during 2023-24."
    },
    {
      "question": "27. India recently launched the trade transaction in rupees with which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Sri Lanka[B] Nepal[C] Bangladesh[D] Myanmar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Bangladesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Bangladesh and India launched the trade transaction in rupees, a move aimed at reducing dependence on the US dollar and strengthening regional currency and trade.\nThis is the first time Bangladesh has done bilateral trade with a foreign country in addition to the US dollar."
    },
    {
      "question": "28. As per the UN data, India lifted how many people out of poverty in the last 15 years?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 11.5 crore[B] 21.5 crore[C] 41.5 crore[D] 61.5 crore"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [41.5 crore]",
      "hint": "Notes:United Nations has said that India has registered remarkable reduction in poverty with 41.5 crore people coming out of it in just 15 years.\nThe UN said, 25 countries, including India, successfully halved their global Multidimensional Poverty Index (MPI) values within 15 years. These 25 countries include Cambodia, China, Congo, Honduras, Indonesia, Morocco, Serbia, and Vietnam besides India."
    },
    {
      "question": "29. What is the Retail inflation, based on Consumer Price Index (CPI), in June 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 4.81 %[B] 5.81 %[C] 6.81 %[D] 8.81 %"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [4.81 %]",
      "hint": "Notes:Retail inflation, based on Consumer Price Index (CPI), stood at 4.81 percent in June this year.\nAccording to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation data, the Consumer Food Price Index (CFPI) for the last month rises to 4.49 percent as compared to 2.91 percent in May, mainly due to a rise in vegetable prices."
    },
    {
      "question": "30. Which Union Ministry launched the ‘Action Taken Report (ATR) Module of AuditOnline’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Panchayati Raj[B] Ministry of Finance[C] Ministry of MSME[D] Ministry of Commerce and Industry"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Panchayati Raj]",
      "hint": "Notes:ATR Module of AuditOnline was launched virtually by Union Minister of State for Panchayati Raj Kapil Moreshwar Patil.\nThe objective of this module is to offer a well-organized method for conducting audits, guaranteeing transparency regarding the steps taken to address audit findings."
    },
    {
      "question": "31. Bhoomi Samman Awards is associated with implementation of which scheme?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Digital India Land Records Modernization Programme[B] Swatch Bharat Mission[C] PM KISAN Yojana[D] PM Fasal Bima Yojana"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Digital India Land Records Modernization Programme]",
      "hint": "Notes:The President of India Droupadi Murmu presented the “Bhoomi Samman” 2023 to State Secretaries and District Collectors along with their teams who have excelled in achieving saturation of the core components of Digital India Land Records Modernization Programme (DILRMP).\nThe awards were presented in a function at New Delhi, organized by Union Ministry of Rural Development."
    },
    {
      "question": "32. Which country has launched an initiative to reduce Clothing Waste by reimbursing cloth repairs?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] France[C] Norway[D] Finland"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [France]",
      "hint": "Notes:In an inventive initiative, France is addressing clothing waste by promoting a novel program that encourages repairing rather than disposing of clothes that are close to being unusable.\nAs part of the program, individuals who opt to repair their clothing will receive reimbursements ranging from €6 to €25 (equivalent to Rs 553 and Rs 2,306) to cover the costs of mending."
    },
    {
      "question": "33. How many people living with HIV globally were unable to obtain HIV treatment?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 2.2 million[B] 4.2 million[C] 7.2 million[D] 9.2 million"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [9.2 million]",
      "hint": "Notes:In 2022, approximately 9.2 million individuals who are living with HIV globally were unable to obtain HIV treatment, as stated in the report titled ‘The Path That Ends AIDS’.\nFurthermore, the report highlighted that even among the 2.1 million people who received treatment, a significant number were not able to achieve viral suppression."
    },
    {
      "question": "34. Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Delhi is to set up offshore campus in which city?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Paris[B] Abu Dhabi[C] Berlin[D] Niger"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Abu Dhabi]",
      "hint": "Notes:IIT Delhi has signed an agreement to establish a campus in Abu Dhabi, UAE, with the aim of promoting educational and research collaborations between India and the UAE.\nThe campus will offer both undergraduate and postgraduate programs in various disciplines. IIT Madras earlier announced a similar venture in Zanzibar, Tanzania."
    },
    {
      "question": "35. Safran Helicopter Engine, which was seen in the news, is an aerospace company of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] Japan[C] France[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [France]",
      "hint": "Notes:India and France have decided to collaborate in development of combat aircraft engine and engines specifically for the Indian Multi Role Helicopter (IMRH) which is a project undertaken by the state-owned Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL).\nIn this regard, HAL and Safran Helicopter Engine have finalized a Shareholders’ Agreement for the development of engines."
    },
    {
      "question": "36. Oommen Chandy, who passed away, was the former Chief Minister of which state/UT?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Tamil Nadu[B] Kerala[C] West Bengal[D] Odisha"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Kerala]",
      "hint": "Notes:Former Kerala Chief Minister Oommen Chandy passes away at the age of 79. He served as the Chief Minister from 2004 to 2006 and 2011 to 2016.\nChandy became active in politics through the Kerala Students Union (KSU) and the Youth Congress.  At the age of 27, Oommen Chandy won the Kerala legislative assembly seat from his constituency, Puthupally. He has also served as Home Minister, Finance Minister and Labour Minister."
    },
    {
      "question": "37. Synchro, which was seen in the news, is associated with which sports?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Shooting[B] Swimming[C] Archery[D] Cricket"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Swimming]",
      "hint": "Notes:Artistic swimming, previously known as synchro, will witness the inclusion of male competitors in the Olympics for the very first time.\nSeveral nations, such as the United States, Japan, Germany, and China, have male swimmers participating in the world championships. Spain and Italy also boast prominent male competitors in the sport."
    },
    {
      "question": "38. Which state has announced toe establish ‘CM Rise’ schools?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Gujarat[B] Madhya Pradesh[C] Maharashtra[D] Assam"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Madhya Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:To ensure the availability of high-quality education, the Madhya Pradesh government has decided to establish 9,000 ‘CM Rise’ schools.\nDuring his visit to Shajapur district, Chief Minister Shivraj Singh Chouhan inaugurated a CM Rise School in Gulana village. He also announced that the school would be dedicated to the renowned jurist and social reformer, Babasaheb Ambedkar."
    },
    {
      "question": "39. Which institution is set to issue SOP for banks to help fast track rupee trade?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Finance[B] Reserve Bank of India[C] National Statistical Office[D] NITI Aayog"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Reserve Bank of India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) is expected to issue a standard operating procedure for banks to issue proofs of inward remittances for exporters.\nIt aims to tide over the hiccups faced by exporters in the rupee-based trading mechanism for foreign trade."
    },
    {
      "question": "40. Which institution unveiled the Techno-Commercial Readiness and Market Maturity Matrix (TCRM Matrix) Framework?",
      "options": [
        "[A] SEBI[B] NITI Aayog[C] NASSCOM[D] BSE"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [NITI Aayog]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Techno-Commercial Readiness and Market Maturity Matrix (TCRM Matrix) Framework was unveiled by NITI Aayog, aiming to foster innovation and entrepreneurship in India.\nIt is an innovative evaluation tool, has been developed to transform technology assessment, promote innovation, and ignite entrepreneurship in India."
    },
    {
      "question": "41. The Export Policy of ‘Non-Basmati White Rice’ has been changed from ‘Free with export duty of 20%’ to which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] State Trading Enterprises[B] Restricted Goods[C] Prohibited Goods[D] Free Goods"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Prohibited Goods]",
      "hint": "Notes:The government has modified the Export Policy of Non-Basmati White Rice to ensure sufficient domestic supply at affordable rates.\nTo guarantee sufficient presence of Non-Basmati White Rice in the Indian market and address the price surge within the country, the Government of India has swiftly changed the Export Policy of this rice variety from ‘Free with export duty of 20%’ to ‘Prohibited,’ taking immediate effect."
    },
    {
      "question": "42. Which state/UT launched the ‘Early childhood care and education (ECCE) kit’ or “Khel Pitara” kits?",
      "options": [
        "[A] New Delhi[B] Uttar Pradesh[C] Bihar[D] Telangana"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [New Delhi]",
      "hint": "Notes:Delhi Chief Minister recently launched the early childhood care and education (ECCE) kit or “Khel Pitara” kits.\nIt was developed by the State Council of Educational Research and Training (SCERT) Delhi and anganwadi team. The kit comprises games, toys, puzzles, and books. They will be distributed across 11,000 Anganwadi centres in Delhi."
    },
    {
      "question": "43. Which state/ UT launched the SC/ST (prevention of transfer of certain lands) (Amendment) Bill?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Madhya Pradesh[B] Karnataka[C] Assam[D] Odisha"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Karnataka]",
      "hint": "Notes:Recently, the Karnataka Legislative Assembly approved the Karnataka SC/ST (prevention of transfer of certain lands) (Amendment) Bill.\nIt aims to clarify the “time limitation” issue related to preventing the transfer of lands allocated to SC/ST communities. The beneficiaries are not subject to any time limitation when approaching courts to seek the restoration of lands allocated to them."
    },
    {
      "question": "44. Which Chief Minister created a record as the second longest-serving Chief Minister in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Mamata Banerjee[B] Naveen Patnaik[C] Pinarayi Vijayan[D] Yogi Adityanath"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Naveen Patnaik]",
      "hint": "Notes:Odisha Chief Minister Naveen Patnaik equals former West Bengal Chief Minister Jyoti Basu’s record as the second longest-serving Chief Minister in India.\nMr Naveen Patnaik has held the position for 23 years and 138 days. The title of the longest-serving CM belongs to Pawan Kumar Chamling, the former CM of Sikkim, who held the position for 24 years and 166 days."
    },
    {
      "question": "45. Which Sea runs between mainland China and the Korean Peninsula?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Yellow Sea[B] Philippine Sea[C] Red Sea[D] Black Sea"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Yellow Sea]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Yellow Sea is a marginal sea of the Western Pacific Ocean located between mainland China and the Korean Peninsula.\nNorth Korea fired ‘several cruise missiles’ into the Yellow Sea between China and the Korean peninsula, the South Korean military reported."
    },
    {
      "question": "46. The first in-person follow-up event of BRICS Urbanisation Forum is set to be organised in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] South Africa[C] Australia[D] Japan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [South Africa]",
      "hint": "Notes:The BRICS Urbanisation Forum, which was initially launched in New Delhi in February 2013, will hold its first in-person follow-up event in Durban, South Africa.\nDuring the two-day conference, representatives from the five BRICS nations will engage in discussions about crucial urban development matters, aiming to explore how cities worldwide are enhancing their resilience to these challenges."
    },
    {
      "question": "47. Which state is to create at least five regional coordination units to identify violations in Coastal Regulation Zone (CRZ) areas?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Goa[B] Tamil Nadu[C] Andhra Pradesh[D] Kerala"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Tamil Nadu State Coastal Zone Management Authority (TNSCZMA) intends to create at least five regional coordination units to establish an efficient system for identifying violations in Coastal Regulation Zone (CRZ) areas, conducting essential monitoring, and taking appropriate actions against such violations.\nThe TNSCZMA has also suggested a significant increase in the scrutiny fee collected from project proponents."
    },
    {
      "question": "48. ‘National Nursing and Midwifery Commission Bill’ is associated with which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Health and Family Welfare[B] Ministry of Home Affairs[C] Ministry of Women and Child Development[D] Ministry of Science and Technology"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Health and Family Welfare]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Lok Sabha has passed the National Nursing and Midwifery Commission Bill, 2023. The bill aims to establish regulations and uphold education and service standards for nursing and midwifery professionals. It comes under the aegis of Ministry of Health and Family Welfare.\nThe National Nursing and Midwifery Commission Bill, 2023 aims at setting up National Nursing and Midwifery Commission (NNMC) and to repeal the Indian Nursing Council Act, 1947."
    },
    {
      "question": "49. ‘Meri Maati Mera Desh’ campaign aims to create a garden in which city?",
      "options": [
        "[A] New Delhi[B] Mumbai[C] Gandhi Nagar[D] Ladakh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [New Delhi]",
      "hint": "Notes:As part of the ‘Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav’ celebration, the Union government has initiated the ‘Meri Maati Mera Desh’ campaign, aimed at creating a garden along the Kartavya Path in Delhi.\nSoil collected from various regions of India in August will be used for this purpose. The campaign includes events at different levels, starting with panchayat-level programs scheduled between August 9 and 15, followed by village, block, urban local body, state, and national-level programs."
    },
    {
      "question": "50. India’s NSIL is scheduled to launch PSLV-C56 mission, with the primary payload of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UAE[B] Singapore[C] Australia[D] Finland"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Singapore]",
      "hint": "Notes:New Space India Ltd (NSIL), the commercial arm of the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO), revealed their second consecutive commercial space mission, named PSLV-C56, which is scheduled to launch on 31 July.\nThe mission’s primary payload is the DS-SAR satellite from Singapore’s Defence Science and Technology Agency (DSTA), intended for satellite imaging applications by Singaporean government agencies."
    }
  ],
  "type": "current-affairs-quiz-july-2023",
  "__v": 0
},
{
  "_id": {
    "$oid": "651556a54a8b33acb2b5b0d4"
  },
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "1. Khongsang railway station, which was seen in the news, is located in which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Manipur[B] Assam[C] Sikkim[D] Arunachal Pradesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Manipur]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Northeast Frontier (NF) Railway in association with the state’s transport department dispatched the first goods trains carrying food grains and essential commodities to Khongsang railway station at Manipur from Guwahati.\nKhongsang is the latest station which was commissioned in 2022 in the Jiribam-Imphal new line project. The first direct passenger train service namely ‘Jan Shatabdi Express’ was earlier inaugurated between Tripura’s Agartala and Khongsang ."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. Which country has officially re-entered the UNESCO?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Russia[C] USA[D] Ukraine"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:U.S. first lady Jill Biden attended a flag-raising ceremony at UNESCO in Paris, marking Washington’s official re-entry into the U.N. agency.\nThe United States had announced its intention to rejoin UNESCO in June, and the organization’s 193 member states earlier this month voted to approve the U.S. re-entry after 5 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Which sports association has been recognised as the official body by the Sports Ministry of India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Handball Association of India[B] Silambam Association[C] Taekwando Association[D] Ringball Association of India"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Handball Association of India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Sports Ministry has decided to recognise the Handball Association of India (HAI) as the official body to run the game in the country.\nRecently the IOA also gave HAI recognition after it agreed to merge with the Handball Federation of India (HFI). India has been preparing for the upcoming Hangzhou Asian Games."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Asian Development Bank (ADB) inked a deal with India for ‘Enhancing Connectivity and Sustainability in Roads Project’ for which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Gujarat[B] Assam[C] Bihar[D] Maharashtra"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Bihar]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Asian Development Bank (ADB) and the Government of India inked a deal for a $295 million loan for the implementation of the Enhancing Connectivity and Sustainability in Bihar Roads Project.\nThe loan aims to enhance approximately 265 kilometers of state highways in Bihar with climate and disaster resilient features, alongside incorporating road safety elements."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. Which country is undertaking the project – Demonstration Rocket for Agile Cislunar Operations?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] China[C] Russia[D] USA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:The National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) of the USA and the U.S. Military have collaborated for a project named Demonstration Rocket for Agile Cislunar Operations (DRACO). The project aims to launch a nuclear-powered satellite to Earth’s orbit in late 2025 or early 2026.\nThe spacecraft for the project is developed by Lockheed Martin. The project involves an in-space test of Nuclear Thermal Propulsion (NPT) technology, marking a significant technical advancement."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which state/ UT saw the highest number of deaths due to rabies in the country in 2022?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Andhra Pradesh[B] West Bengal[C] New Delhi[D] Maharashtra"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [New Delhi]",
      "hint": "Notes:As per the information given by the Health Ministry in the Lok Sabha this week, Delhi saw the highest number of deaths due to rabies in the country in 2022.\nWhile Delhi reported 48 fatalities, West Bengal saw 38 deaths, followed by Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, Maharashtra at 29 each."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Which country has granted Pakistan a two-year rollover on USD 2.4 billion loan?",
      "options": [
        "[A] China[B] USA[C] Russia[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [China]",
      "hint": "Notes:China has granted Pakistan a two-year rollover on a USD 2.4-billion loan for a period of two years.\nThis move is expected to provide relief to Pakistan, which is facing a severe Balance of Payments crisis. Its current reserves barely cover two months’ worth of import bills."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Which country grants stapled visas to Indian nationals from Arunachal Pradesh and Jammu and Kashmir?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Myanmar[B] China[C] Bangladesh[D] Afghanistan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [China]",
      "hint": "Notes:A stapled visa is an unstamped paper attached to a passport page using a pin or staples, which can be easily torn off or removed as desired.\nChina has adopted a policy of granting stapled visas to Indian nationals from Arunachal Pradesh, Ladakh and Jammu and Kashmir. While China considers these visas as valid documents, the Government of India has consistently rejected this stance."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Western Tragopan is the state Bird for which Indian State?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Uttar Pradesh[B] Himachal Pradesh[C] Tamil Nadu[D] Kerala"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Himachal Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Western Tragopan (Tragopan-melanocephalus) is the Himachal Pradesh’s state bird. It has been reported that the species is experiencing habitat loss in certain regions of the country.\nHowever, due to the dedicated efforts of the state authorities, there has been a steady rise in the population of this endangered species at the State’s Sarahan pheasantry, the conservation breeding center, providing hope for its survival and future expansion."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. Where is the ‘World Police and Fire Games 2023’ held?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Australia[C] Japan[D] Canada"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Canada]",
      "hint": "Notes:The 2023 World Police and Fire Games is a community-wide sports event that is held from July 28 – August 6, 2023 at Winnipeg, Canada.\nIndia is represented by the Central Reserve Police Force (CRPF), and the athletes of CRPF bagged five gold and one silver medal for India on the first day of the event."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. Which Indian city is the host of the ‘SemiconIndia 2023 conference’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Mumbai[B] Pune[C] Bengaluru[D] Gandhi Nagar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Gandhi Nagar]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Ministry of Electronics and IT (MeitY) added two semiconductor design startups, Aheesa Digital Innovations, and Calligo Technologies, to the SemiconIndia futureDESIGN DLI scheme.\nThis was announced during the 2nd edition of the SemiconIndia 2023 conference in Gandhinagar. These startups/MSMEs will receive support under the scheme."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. As part of second phase of CPEC, China signed six agreements with which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] Pakistan[C] USA[D] Russia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Pakistan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Pakistan and China ink six agreements to help undertake the second phase of the USD 60 billion China-Pakistan Economic Corridor (CPEC) projects under a new model.\nPrime Minister Shehbaz Sharif and Chinese Vice Premier He Lifeng witnessed the signing ceremony to mark 10 years of the CPEC. The CPEC, which connects Gwadar Port in Pakistan’s Balochistan with China’s Xinjiang province, is opposed by India as it is being laid through Pakistan-occupied Kashmir."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. ‘MPOWER Measures’, which are seen in the news, are associated with which organisation?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UN Women[B] World Health Organization[C] World Bank[D] International Monetary Fund"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [World Health Organization]",
      "hint": "Notes:A new World Health Organization (WHO) report revealed that over the past 15 years, 71% of the global population, approximately 5.6 billion people, are now protected by at least one of the measures, five times more than in 2007.\nThe WHO’s MPOWER measures aim to monitor tobacco use and prevention policies, protect people from tobacco smoke, provide assistance to quit tobacco, warn about the dangers of tobacco, enforce bans on tobacco advertising, and raise taxes on tobacco products."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. What is DCS, that has been launched by the Union Agricultural Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Digital Crop Survey[B] Durable Crop Survey[C] Doubling Crop Survey[D] Distributive Crop Survey"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Digital Crop Survey]",
      "hint": "Notes:To improve the collection of sowing data, the government has initiated a pilot project called Digital Crop Survey (DCS) in 12 states starting from the Kharif season of 2023.\nThe DCS reference application uses technologies like GIS and GPS, and aims to ensure accurate crop area estimation and support farmers with solutions. It has been created as a publicly available open-source and interoperable tool, adhering to open standards."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. What is AU Microscopii, which was seen in the news?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Bacterium[B] Star[C] Asteroid[D] Microscope"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Star]",
      "hint": "Notes:NASA’ s Hubble Space Telescope has detected a series of energetic eruptions at a nearby red dwarf star, known as AU Microscopii.\nThe dwarf star is situated approximately 32 light years away from the Sun. AU Microscopii is approximately 23 million years old."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Civitavecchia, which was seen in the news, is a city in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Sri Lanka[B] Italy[C] Myanmar[D] Papua New Guinea"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Italy]",
      "hint": "Notes:Italian authorities from the Carabinieri Command for the Protection of Cultural Heritage reported the discovery of an ancient cargo ship wreckage off the port in Civitavecchia, near Rome.\nThe ship, dating back to the 1st or 2nd century BC, contains hundreds of well-preserved Roman jars, known as amphorae, found using a remotely operated robot."
    },
    {
      "question": "17. What is India’s GST collection for the month of July 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Rs 1.05 lakh crore[B] Rs 1.15 lakh crore[C] Rs 1.65 lakh crore[D] Rs 1.95 lakh crore"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Rs 1.65 lakh crore]",
      "hint": "Notes:India’s gross revenues from the Goods and Services Tax (GST) hit a three-month high to cross ₹1.65 lakh crore in July 2023. July’s collections were 2.2% higher than the previous month’s GST collection.\nHowever, at 10.8%, it was the slowest uptick in collections since July 2021 compared to revenues from the same month last year."
    },
    {
      "question": "18. ‘Article 117 of the Constitution’ pertains to which field?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Financial Bill[B] Language to be used in Parliament[C] Salaries of Judges[D] Freedom of speech in Parliament"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Financial Bill]",
      "hint": "Notes:Article 117 of the Constitution pertains to the specific provisions concerning financial Bills. A Bill that addresses any of the matters mentioned in clauses of Article 110 (1) can only be introduced or proposed in the Lok Sabha based on the President’s recommendation and cannot be introduced in the Rajya Sabha.\nIt was recently stated that the Digital Personal Data Protection (DPDP) Bill is categorized as a regular Bill and not a money bill, contrary to earlier reports."
    },
    {
      "question": "19. The Government of NCT of Delhi Bill proposes to constitute which institution?",
      "options": [
        "[A] National Capital Civil Service Authority[B] National Capital Authority[C] National Capital Government Affairs Authority[D] National Capital Chief Secretary Authority"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [National Capital Civil Service Authority]",
      "hint": "Notes:Parliament has passed the Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi (Amendment) Bill 2023. The Rajya Sabha cleared it by voting 131 MPs in favour of the bill, while 102 MPs against bill.\nIt empowers the Central Government to make rules in connection with the affairs of the Government of Delhi. It also has a provision of the constitution of the National Capital Civil Service Authority, consisting of Delhi Chief Minister, the Chief Secretary of Delhi, and the Principal Home Secretary of Delhi."
    },
    {
      "question": "20. India provides financial assistance of Rs 45 crore to support digital identity project of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Bangladesh[B] Sri Lanka[C] Laos[D] Cambodia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Sri Lanka]",
      "hint": "Notes:India has handed over ₹45 crore in advance to Sri Lanka to fund its unique digital identity project.\nIt constitutes 15 per cent of the total funds required for the successful implementation of the project as an advance payment. The project aims to collect biographic and biometric information, including facial, iris, and fingerprint data, which will be stored in a centralised system."
    },
    {
      "question": "21. If a breach of privilege is believed to have committed by Members of Parliament, a motion will be referred to which committee?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Privileges Committee[B] Parliamentary Committee[C] Priority Committee[D] Prime Members Committee"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Privileges Committee]",
      "hint": "Notes:Parliamentary privilege grants specific rights to Members of Parliament, including freedom of expression during debates without the risk of court proceedings. If a breach of privilege is believed to have occurred, any member can raise a motion that will be referred to the Privileges Committee.\nRecently, Rajya Sabha Chairman Jagdeep Dhankhar has referred complaints concerning the privilege of the House against TMC’s Derek O’Brien and AAP’s Raghav Chadha to the privileges committee."
    },
    {
      "question": "22. Which Indian chess player overtook Viswanathan Anand as the highest-rated Indian chess player in FIDE rankings?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Praggnananda[B] Gukesh[C] Arjun Erigaisi[D] Nihal Sarin"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Gukesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:Grandmaster D. Gukesh overtook Viswanathan Anand as the highest-rated Indian chess player in FIDE rankings. He is the second-youngest Grandmaster (GM) globally and the youngest Indian to achieve this feat.\nGukesh became the number one chess player in India after posting a win against Misratdin Iskandarov of Azerbaijan in the World Cup in Baku, Azerbaijan."
    },
    {
      "question": "23. India provides financial assistance of Rs 45 crore to support digital identity project of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Bangladesh[B] Sri Lanka[C] Laos[D] Cambodia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Sri Lanka]",
      "hint": "Notes:India has handed over ₹45 crore in advance to Sri Lanka to fund its unique digital identity project.\nIt constitutes 15 per cent of the total funds required for the successful implementation of the project as an advance payment. The project aims to collect biographic and biometric information, including facial, iris, and fingerprint data, which will be stored in a centralised system."
    },
    {
      "question": "24. Which Indian player finished as runner-up at the Australian Open badminton tournament?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Lakshya Sen[B] HS Prannoy[C] K Srikanth[D] Chirag Shetty"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [HS Prannoy]",
      "hint": "Notes:India’s HS Prannoy finished runner-up at the Australian Open Super 500 badminton tournament after losing a three-game thriller to China’s Weng Hong Yang in the men’s singles finals.\nThe 31-year-old player from Kerala had beaten Weng in a three-game play to claim the Malaysia Masters in May."
    },
    {
      "question": "25. Which Indian has been chosen as the vice-chair of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Raman Sukumar[B] Renee Borges[C] Raghavendra Gadagkar[D] Aparna Watve"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Raman Sukumar]",
      "hint": "Notes:During the election at the United Nations Environment Programme headquarters in Nairobi, Raman Sukumar, an expert on the Asian elephant, was chosen as a vice-chair of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC).\nHis appointment was specifically for the position of Working Group II Vice-Chair within the newly formed IPCC Bureau, which encompasses 34 members including the Chair and three Vice-Chairs."
    },
    {
      "question": "26. Which institution is developing the ‘Organ Donation Registry’ in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] NHA[B] NMC[C] AIIMS[D] IMA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [NHA]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Organ Donation Registry is being developed by the National Health Authority (NHA) and the union health ministry following consultation with the NITI Aayog for an overhaul of the National Organ Tissue Transplantation Organization.\nIt aims to enhance transparency and efficiency in organ transplantation. This initiative, developed in collaboration with NITI Aayog, aims to revamp the National Organ Tissue Transplantation Organization (NOTTO) to eliminate intermediaries."
    },
    {
      "question": "27. India’s Defence Ministry has decided to replace Microsoft Operating System with which Operating system?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Maya[B] macOS[C] Kuku[D] Haiku"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Maya]",
      "hint": "Notes:India’s Defence Ministry has decided to replace Microsoft Operating System (OS) in all its computers that can connect to the Internet with Maya.\nMaya, which has been developed by Indian government agencies within six months, and is aimed at preventing malware attacks by cybercriminals. The new OS will be backed by a protection system called Chakravyuh."
    },
    {
      "question": "28. Who became the fastest Indian cricketer to clinch 50 wickets in T20 Internationals?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Jasprit Bumrah[B] R Ashwin[C] Kuldeep Yadav[D] Ravindra Jadeja"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Kuldeep Yadav]",
      "hint": "Notes:Left-arm spinner Kuldeep Yadav became the fastest Indian to clinch 50 wickets in T20 Internationals in terms of number of matches played.\nKuldeep achieved the feat in his 30th T20I match for India, surpassing teammate Yuzvendra Chahal, who had 50 T20I wickets in 34 games."
    },
    {
      "question": "29. Where is the ‘Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) Academy’ located in which city?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Mussoorie[B] Ghaziabad[C] New Delhi[D] Pune"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ghaziabad]",
      "hint": "Notes:Recently, the Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) Academy in Ghaziabad became the tenth member of the Interpol Global Academy Network.\nThis inclusion will facilitate the creation and execution of combined training initiatives and research endeavors."
    },
    {
      "question": "30. Coastal Aquaculture Authority (Amendment) Bill, 2023 is associated with which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Defence[B] Ministry of Fisheries, Animal Husbandry and Dairying[C] Ministry of Jal Shakti[D] Ministry of External Affairs"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Ministry of Fisheries, Animal Husbandry and Dairying]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Coastal Aquaculture Authority (Amendment) Bill, 2023 seeks to remove criminal penalties for violations in coastal aquaculture practices, promoting a more business-friendly environment.\nThe bill aims to broaden its range, address regulatory inconsistencies, and lessen compliance requirements, all while maintaining environmental safeguards in coastal regions."
    },
    {
      "question": "31. Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana (Urban) is implemented by which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Housing and Urban Affairs[B] Ministry of Home Affairs[C] Ministry of Finance[D] Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Housing and Urban Affairs]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Union Housing and Urban Affairs Ministry is underway with the implementation of the Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana (Urban), originally launched in 2015. The scheme aims to build affordable houses in Urban India.\nThe Prime Minister, on August 15, 2023, announced another scheme for the urban middle class, aimed to ease the process of acquiring and constructing a home of their own."
    },
    {
      "question": "32. Which meeting, under India’s presidency, led to a consensus on setting up a global initiative on digital health led by WHO?",
      "options": [
        "[A] BRICS[B] G-20[C] G-7[D] ASEAN"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [G-20]",
      "hint": "Notes:During India’s ongoing G20 presidency, India has managed to build consensus on two of the most contentious priority areas for the health track – creating a research and manufacturing network for vaccines, therapeutics, and diagnostics, and setting up a platform / global initiative for digital health\nThis platform is expected to focus on equitable research and development in manufacturing of vaccines, drugs, and diagnostics."
    },
    {
      "question": "33. Which country has approved a law which permits purchase and possession of cannabis for recreational use?",
      "options": [
        "[A] India[B] China[C] Germany[D] USA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Germany]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Government of Germany has recently approved a draft law which permits individuals to purchase and possess cannabis for recreational use. Under the draft law, adults can possess up to 25 grams (0.9 ounces) of cannabis and grow up to three plants for personal use.\nThe draft further states that people will also be allowed to join non-profit “cannabis clubs” of up to 500 members where the drug can be legally cultivated and purchased."
    },
    {
      "question": "34. Which institution issued guidelines to banks and NBFCs not to levy penal interest on borrowers in case of default?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Finance[B] RBI[C] NITI Aayog[D] Supreme Court of India"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [RBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) issued a fresh set of guidelines for banks and other regulated entities (REs) on the imposition of penal charges on loan borrowers.\nIt was reported that many banks use penal rate of interest, over and above the applicable interest rates, in case of defaults / non-compliance by the borrower with the terms on which credit facilities were sanctioned. The guidelines will be effective from January 1, 2024."
    },
    {
      "question": "35. What is ‘NBRI Namoh 108’, which has been developed by CSIR-NBRI?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Cotton[B] Lotus[C] Rice[D] Mango"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Lotus]",
      "hint": "Notes:Union Minister of State (IC) Science and Technology Jitendra Singh unveiled the new variety Lotus flower which has 108 petals.\nThe lotus named ‘NBRI Namoh 108’ is developed by the CSIR-National Botanical Research Institute (NBRI), based in Lucknow."
    },
    {
      "question": "36. Which state is set to conduct ‘Comprehensive survey of state’s disaster-prone cities’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Gujarat[B] Uttarakhand[C] Assam[D] West Bengal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Uttarakhand]",
      "hint": "Notes:Uttarakhand government is set to conduct a comprehensive survey of disaster-prone cities and towns.\nUttarakhand Landslide Mitigation and Management Centre announced that Geophysical and geo-mapping investigation of cities will be part of the survey. In January this year, the land subsidence crisis in Joshimath grabbed national attention."
    },
    {
      "question": "37. What is the recent rating on India, as per Moody’s Investors Service?",
      "options": [
        "[A] BBB[B] Baa3[C] Ba2[D] BB"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Baa3]",
      "hint": "Notes:Moody’s Investors Service affirmed its Baa3 rating on India and maintained the stable outlook, but warned of political issues and even cited the example of the ongoing violence in Manipur.\nThe rating agency said the affirmation of India’s rating and stable outlook was driven by its view that the economy is set to grow rapidly by international standards, although potential growth has declined in the last 7-10 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "38. Which institution has recently approved USD 25 million proposal submitted by the India’s Department of Animal Husbandry & Dairying?",
      "options": [
        "[A] AIIB[B] World Bank[C] G20 Pandemic Fund[D] NDB"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [G20 Pandemic Fund]",
      "hint": "Notes:The G20 Pandemic Fund has approved a $25 million proposal submitted by India’s Department of Animal Husbandry & Dairying, Ministry of Fisheries, Animal Husbandry & Dairying (DAHD), Government of India on “Animal Health Security Strengthening in India for Pandemic Preparedness and Response”.\nThe G20 Pandemic Fund was established under Indonesia’s G20 Presidency, which finances critical investments to strengthen pandemic prevention, preparedness, and response capacities at national, regional, and global levels of low- and middle-income countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "39. The African Union has suspended which country until ‘the effective restoration of constitutional order’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Egypt[B] Niger[C] Kenya[D] South Africa"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Niger]",
      "hint": "Notes:The African Union suspended Niger from all its institutions and activities “until the effective restoration of constitutional order” following last month’s coup.\nThe Executive Council of the 55-nation bloc made the decision after the soldiers overthrew Niger’s democratically elected president almost four weeks ago and placed themselves in power. President Mohamed Bazoum and his family have been kept under house arrest in the capital, Niamey."
    },
    {
      "question": "40. Madras is the old name of the capital city of which Indian state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kerala[B] Tamil Nadu[C] Karnataka[D] Andhra Pradesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:August 22 is annually celebrated as Madras Day, to commemorate the foundation day of the city of Madras (now Chennai).\nIt was on this day in 1639 that the town of Madrasapatnam, was purchased by the East India Company (EIC) from local kings. After 1947, the state and the city continued to be referred to as Madras. It was carved out of the Madras presidency that covered parts of other South- Indian states. In 1969, the state was officially renamed Tamil Nadu and in 1996, the capital city of Madras became Chennai."
    },
    {
      "question": "41. Indian Coast Guard signed a MoU with its counterpart of which country, on enhanced maritime cooperation, for the first time?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Philippines[B] Maldives[C] Sri Lanka[D] France"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Philippines]",
      "hint": "Notes:Indian Coast Guard has signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with Philippine Coast Guard (PCG) on enhanced maritime cooperation.\nBoth the sides held their first bilateral meeting on a range of maritime issues. The MoU inked seeks to enhance the professional linkage between the two Coast Guards in the domain of Maritime Law Enforcement (MLE), Maritime Search and Rescue (M-SAR) and Marine Pollution Response (MPR)."
    },
    {
      "question": "42. Indian banking system liquidity slipped into a deficit in which month of 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] April[B] May[C] July[D] August"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [August]",
      "hint": "Notes:Indian banking system liquidity slipped into a deficit in which month of August since end-March, as the Reserve Bank of India’s (RBI) temporary liquidity withdrawal and tax outflows impacted banks’ funding.\nBanking system liquidity stood at a deficit of 236 billion rupees ($2.84 billion) as of Aug. 21, according to RBI data. Liquidity surplus had hit a 13-month high of 2.8 trillion rupees at the start of the month, which has been dropping since then."
    },
    {
      "question": "43. Madras is the old name of the capital city of which Indian state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kerala[B] Tamil Nadu[C] Karnataka[D] Andhra Pradesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:August 22 is annually celebrated as Madras Day, to commemorate the foundation day of the city of Madras (now Chennai).\nIt was on this day in 1639 that the town of Madrasapatnam, was purchased by the East India Company (EIC) from local kings. After 1947, the state and the city continued to be referred to as Madras. It was carved out of the Madras presidency that covered parts of other South- Indian states. In 1969, the state was officially renamed Tamil Nadu and in 1996, the capital city of Madras became Chennai."
    },
    {
      "question": "44. Which Union Ministry launched the ‘Khadi Rakshasoot’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises[B] Ministry of Home Affairs[C] Ministry of Women and Child Development[D] Ministry of Commerce and Industry"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises]",
      "hint": "Notes:Khadi and Village Industries Commission (KVIC) has launched ‘Khadi Rakshasoot’ to commemorate the Raksha Bandhan in New Delhi.\nThis ‘Khadi Rakshasoot’ (Khadi-Rakhi) was introduced under the aegis of Ministry of Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises. This product is entirely natural, devoid of any chemical additives. This year ‘Khadi Rakshasoot’ is being introduced as a ‘Pilot Project’ initiative available exclusively at Khadi Bhawan, in New Delhi."
    },
    {
      "question": "45. Which Union Ministry is associated with ‘Mera Bill Mera Adhikaar initiative’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Finance[B] Ministry of Corporate Affairs[C] Ministry of MSME[D] Ministry of Commerce and Industry"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Finance]",
      "hint": "Notes:To promote the practice of customers requesting invoices or bills for all purchases, the Government of India is introducing the ‘Invoice Incentive Scheme’ known as ‘Mera Bill Mera Adhikaar’ in collaboration with State Governments.\nThe Scheme will be launched on September 1, 2023. The initiative will apply to all business-to-consumer invoices provided to customers by GST-registered suppliers in participating states. A lucky draw must have at least Rs 200 worth of invoices to qualify."
    },
    {
      "question": "46. G20 Pandemic Fund granted USD 25 million to which country’s animal husbandry and dairying department?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Indonesia[B] India[C] Sri Lanka[D] Bangladesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The G20 Pandemic Fund has granted USD 25 million to India’s animal husbandry and dairying department to aid pandemic preparedness and response.\nAccording to the Ministry of fisheries, animal husbandry & dairying, this funding will improve India’s animal health system, a crucial part of the One Health approach for pandemic prevention."
    },
    {
      "question": "47. Which country’s Prime Minister was granted the ‘Grand Cross of the Order of Honour’ by Greece in 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] China[B] USA[C] Ukraine[D] India"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:The President of Greece, Katerina Sakellaropoulou conferred Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi with The Grand Cross of the Order of Honour. The Order of Honour was established in 1975.\nThe Honour is conferred by the President of Greece to Prime Ministers and eminent personalities who by reason of their distinguished position, have contributed to enhancing the stature of Greece."
    },
    {
      "question": "48. Which state launched the ‘Manav Sampada Portal’ to instill transparency in administrative procedures?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Bihar[B] Gujarat[C] Uttar Pradesh[D] Andhra Pradesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Uttar Pradesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Uttar Pradesh Government launched the ‘Manav Sampada Portal’ aiming to instil transparency in administrative procedures.\nThis initiative, according to an official statement, intends to bring the “activities of officers and employees from various departments into the public domain through the portal”. Pertinent details concerning their appointments, leave management, transfers, and retirements will be accessible on the platform."
    },
    {
      "question": "49. ‘Emmerson Mnangagwa’ was re-elected as the President of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Singapore[B] Zimbabwe[C] South Africa[D] Argentina"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Zimbabwe]",
      "hint": "Notes:Zimbabwe’s President Emmerson Mnangagwa has been recently elected for second and final five-year term.\nThe South African country of 16 million population, has a history of election irregularities, and such tactics helped Robert Mugabe, a liberation leader turned autocrat, maintain power for nearly four decades."
    },
    {
      "question": "50. The Embassy of India in which country has launched a mobile application, ‘EoIBh-Connect’ to ease Consular Access?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Singapore[B] UK[C] Canada[D] Bahrain"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Bahrain]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Embassy of India in Bahrain launched a mobile application, EoIBh-Connect, designed to facilitate online appointment booking for a spectrum of consular and visa services, accessible through both the Indian Embassy at Manama, Bahrain.\nThe app has swiftly broadened its capabilities, now enabling users to conveniently schedule appointments with IVS Global."
    }
  ],
  "type": "current-affairs-quiz-august-2023",
  "__v": 0
},
{
  "_id": {
    "$oid": "651556a74a8b33acb2b5b0d6"
  },
  "data": [
    {
      "question": "1. Which city hosted the recent meeting of Western Zonal Council?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Mumbai[B] Gandhinagar[C] Jodhpur[D] Amritsar"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Gandhinagar]",
      "hint": "Notes:Union Home Minister Amit Shah recently chaired 26th meeting of Western Zonal Council at Gandhinagar, Gujarat.\nHe also inaugurated an e-Resource web portal of Inter State Council Secretariat, Ministry of Home Affairs. This portal will facilitate functioning of Zonal Councils. The meeting was attended by Chief Ministers of Gujarat, Maharashtra, Goa and Administrator of Dadra & Nagar Haveli and Daman & Diu."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. Terry Gou, who is to run as Taiwan’s Presidential candidate, is the founder of which company?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Foxconn[B] Samsung[C] Kia[D] Ali pay"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Foxconn]",
      "hint": "Notes:Terry Gou, who founded Apple supplier Foxconn, has announced that he will run as an independent candidate in Taiwan’s presidential election.\nThe country’s Presidential elections are scheduled to take place in September this year. Foxconn, formally known as Hon Hai Precision Industry Co., is a major supplier to Apple and has many factories in China that manufacture iPhones."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Which state implements the ‘Mukhyamantri Chiranjeevi Swasthya Bima Yojana’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Rajasthan[B] Karnataka[C] Assam[D] West Bengal"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Rajasthan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Rajasthan Chief Minister Ashok Gehlot has approved an increase in minimum wages for labourers by Rs 26 per day. This increase would be effective from January 1, 2023.\nHe also announced that registered insured employees and their dependent families under the Employees State Insurance (ESI) Scheme of Rajasthan will also get the benefit of Mukhyamantri Chiranjeevi Swasthya Bima Yojana under the ESI category."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Who has been chosen as the chair of groups of ministers (GoMs) on GST System Reforms?",
      "options": [
        "[A] P Chidambaram[B] Subramaniam Swamy[C] Ajit Pawar[D] Adhir Ranjan Chowdhary"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Ajit Pawar]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Goods and Services Tax (GST) Council has reconstituted two of its groups of ministers (GoMs) tasked with identifying necessary System Reforms to curb evasion and analysing the revenue trends from the 6-year-old indirect tax regime.\nMaharashtra Deputy Chief Minister Ajit Pawar is back at the helm of the GoM on GST System Reforms, replacing his colleague Devendra Fadnavis."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. What is India’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) percent in the April-June quarter of the current fiscal (2023-2024)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 5.8 per cent[B] 6.8 per cent[C] 7.8 per cent[D] 8.8 per cent"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [7.8 per cent]",
      "hint": "Notes:India’s Gross Domestic Product (GDP) registered a growth of 7.8 percent in the April-June quarter of the current fiscal (2023-2024), compared to a growth of 6.1 percent in the previous January-March quarter of fiscal 2022-23.\nAccording to official data shared by the National Statistical Office, India’s nominal GDP or GDP at Current Prices in the first quarter showed a growth rate of 8 percent as compared to 27.7 percent in the previous year’s first quarter."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Which Indian chess player replaced Viswanathan Anand as the country’s top-ranked player?",
      "options": [
        "[A] R Praggnananda[B] D Gukesh[C] Nihal Sarin[D] Arjun Erigaisi"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [D Gukesh]",
      "hint": "Notes:17-year-old D Gukesh took over as the country’s top-ranked player from Viswanathan Anand in FIDE’s monthly rankings list.\nIt has been 37 years since anyone other than Anand holding the top position. The five-time World champion is currently ranked ninth, a spot below Gukesh on the world list, is semi-retired from active chess."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. ‘Rashtriya Poshan Maah’ is observed in which month in India?",
      "options": [
        "[A] August[B] September[C] October[D] November"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [September]",
      "hint": "Notes:Ministry of Women and Child Development is celebrating the 6th Rashtriya Poshan Maah throughout September 2023.\nSeveral activities are organised across the country with themes like ‘Improving Nutrition through Mission LiFE & ‘Exclusive Breastfeeding & Complimentary Feeding’."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Tharman Shanmugaratnam has been elected as President of which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Singapore[B] Malaysia[C] Maldives[D] Mauritius"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Singapore]",
      "hint": "Notes:Tharman Shanmugaratnam is the president-elect of Singapore. He was born on February 25, 1957. He is a popular politician who has won several parliamentary elections. In 2023, he resigned from all government positions and the PAP to run for the Singaporean presidential election. He won the election with 70.4% of the votes.\nShanmugaratnam was previously the Senior Minister of Singapore from 2019 to 2023. He also served as Deputy Prime Minister for eight years. He studied at the London School of Economics, Cambridge University, and Harvard University."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. What is the name of the seventh and last stealth frigate of Project 17A, that was recently launched?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kailashgiri[B] Mahendragiri[C] Sivagiri[D] Bharatgiri"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Mahendragiri]",
      "hint": "Notes:The seventh and last stealth frigate of Project 17A, Mahendragiri, was launched at Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders Ltd. (MDL) in Mumbai.\nUnder Project 17A, a total of seven ships were constructed, four at Mazagon Dock Shipbuilders Ltd. , Mumbai and three at Garden Reach Ship Builders Limited (GRSE), Kolkata."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. Which city is the host of ‘International Aerospace Conference’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Pune[B] Gwalior[C] Bengaluru[D] Hyderabad"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Gwalior]",
      "hint": "Notes:‘International Aerospace Conference: Moving Towards Inclusive Global Value Chains’ was jointly organised by the Ministry of Civil Aviation and Confederation of Indian Industry (CII) in Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh.\nIt is a G20 initiative in the aerospace sector under G20 and B20 priority, focusing on developing inclusive global value chains for Global trade and Investment and aims to promote and strengthen trade and investment among the G20 countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. ‘International Literacy Day’ is observed on which day?",
      "options": [
        "[A] July 8[B] August 8[C] September 8[D] October 8"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [September 8]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Government of India has decided to organise a literacy week from 1st September to 8th September 2023 to celebrate International Literacy Day.\nUNESCO will celebrate International Literacy Day (ILD) on 8 September 2023 under the theme ‘Promoting literacy for a world in transition: Building the foundation for sustainable and peaceful societies’."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. Which country has launched a new type of frigate named the Type 054B?",
      "options": [
        "[A] China[B] USA[C] Russia[D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [China]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Chinese People’s Liberation Army (PLA) Navy has launched a new type of frigate, the Type 054B, China’s Ministry of National Defense.\nType 054B is the larger and more advanced version of Type 054A, which currently forms the backbone of the PLAN (People’s Liberation Army Navy)."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. Which country recorded the highest average temperature in 125 years at 40C?",
      "options": [
        "[A] China[B] UK[C] Germany[D] Japan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Japan]",
      "hint": "Notes:Japan’s average temperature in 2023 summer was the highest since records began 125 years ago, according to the country’s weather agency.\nThe average temperature from June to August was 1.76 degrees Celsius higher than the 30-year average. Earlier in August, Japan recorded the hottest day of the year as temperatures hit 40C in the Fukushima Prefecture."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Which company has launched ‘ALT ID’ solution for guest checkout transactions?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Paytm[B] PhonePe[C] Mastercard[D] VISA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Mastercard]",
      "hint": "Notes:Mastercard, technology company in the payments industry, has launched ALT ID solution for guest checkout transactions.\nALT ID is a custom-made capability to create an alternate identifier for the real card numbers provided by cardholders during guest checkout transactions on e-commerce platforms."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. Which scheme has been granted National Award for e-Governance 2023 (Gold) for Application of Emerging Technologies?",
      "options": [
        "[A] PM KISAN[B] SVAMITVA[C] Atmanirbhar Bharat Abhiyan[D] Mission Karmayogi"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [SVAMITVA]",
      "hint": "Notes:SVAMITVA (Survey of Villages Abadi and Mapping with Improvised Technology in Village Areas) Scheme of Ministry of Panchayati Raj has been conferred with the prestigious National Award for e-Governance 2023 (Gold) for Application of Emerging Technologies for Providing Citizen Centric Services.\nIt was granted at the 26th National Conference on e-Governance (NCeG) organized by the Department of Administrative Reforms and Public Grievances (DARPG), Government of India in Indore."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Who is the chair of the Committee set up to assess the viability of the “one nation, one election” concept?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Amit Shah[B] Ranjan Gogoi[C] Ramnath Kovind[D] Pratibha Patil"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Ramnath Kovind]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Union government has formed a committee under former President Ram Nath Kovind to assess the viability of the “one nation, one election” concept.\nThe members of the panel include Union home minister Amit Shah, ex-J&K chief minister Ghulam Nabi Azad, former Finance Commission chairman N K Singh, Constitution expert Subhash C Kashyap, senior advocate Harish Salve, and ex-Chief Vigilance Commissioner Sanjay Kothari."
    },
    {
      "question": "17. Which country has emerged champions in the Men’s Hockey5s Asia Cup?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Pakistan[B] India[C] Sri Lanka[D] Bangladesh"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [India]",
      "hint": "Notes:India emerged champions in the Men’s Hockey5s Asia Cup, beating arch-rivals Pakistan 2-0 in a shootout after both teams were locked at 4-4 in regulation time.\nWith the win, India have booked their place in the FIH Men’s Hockey5s World Cup 2024."
    },
    {
      "question": "18. MQ-9B Predator Drone, that was in news recently, was developed by which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Israel [B] Russia [C] United States [D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [United States ]",
      "hint": "Notes:India is finalizing a Letter of Request (LoR) to the US government to acquire 31 MQ-9B Predator drones from General Atomics. These drones, a variant of the MQ-9 “Reaper,” offer remote or autonomous flight capabilities and also carry strike missiles for precise target elimination. Developed by General Atomics, the MQ-9B comes in two versions, SkyGuardian and SeaGuardian. The Indian Navy already operates the MQ-9B Sea Guardian since 2020. With a payload of up to 5,670 kg, the drone can fly above 40,000 feet for 40 hours, making it valuable for surveillance, warfare, and expeditionary roles, including integration into civil airspace."
    },
    {
      "question": "19. ‘Kinzhal Missile’, that was recently making news, is developed by which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] USA[B] France[C] Russia [D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Russia ]",
      "hint": "Notes:The first Su-34 bomber crew to launch a Kinzhal missile in Ukraine received state awards. The Kh-47M2, known as “Kinzhal” (Dagger), is a Russian air-launched hypersonic ballistic missile capable of carrying conventional or nuclear warheads with a 480 kg payload, including a 10-50 kt thermonuclear option. It achieves speeds up to Mach 10 (12,350 km/hr) and has a range of 1,500-2,000 km. With an 8 m length, 1 m body diameter, and 4,300 kg launch weight, it’s launched from MiG-31 jets at 18 km altitude, maneuvering throughout its flight to evade air defense."
    },
    {
      "question": "20. What is the conservation status of “Stump Tailed Macaque”, as per the IUCN Red List?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Near Threatened[B] Endangered[C] Critically Endangered[D] Vulnerable"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Vulnerable]",
      "hint": "Notes:Eight stump-tailed macaques were recently relocated to the Delhi Zoo from Aizawl Zoological Park in Mizoram. Also known as bear macaques, these monkeys belong to the Old-World monkey species, Macaca arctoides. They are primarily found in the tropical and subtropical evergreen forests of South Asia.\nTheir natural habitat spans Cambodia, southwest China, northeast India, Laos, Myanmar, northwest Peninsular Malaysia, Thailand, and Vietnam. In India, they inhabit regions south of the Brahmaputra River, including Assam, Meghalaya, eastern Arunachal Pradesh, Nagaland, Manipur, Mizoram, and Tripura. Stump-tailed macaques sport thick, dark brown fur, short tails (3.2-69 mm), and distinctive pink or red faces that darken as they age. Males are larger than females, with longer canine teeth used for social dominance. Their diet comprises fruits, leaves, seeds, insects, and small animals, often stored in cheek pouches. They move primarily on the ground due to limited tree agility. These macaques are classified as Vulnerable on the IUCN Red List and are protected under India’s Wildlife (Protection) Act of 1972 (Schedule II). Conservation efforts are crucial to safeguard their population."
    },
    {
      "question": "21. The Viability Gap Funding for development of BESS aims to generate 4,000 MWh of BESS projects by?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 2024-25[B] 2030-31[C] 2035-36[D] 2040-41"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [2030-31]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Union Cabinet has approved the Scheme for Viability Gap Funding (VGF) aimed at fostering the development of Battery Energy Storage Systems (BESS).\nThis scheme aspires to generate 4,000 MWh of BESS projects by 2030-31, backed by up to 40% capital cost support in the form of VGF. the scheme seeks to provide clean, reliable, and cost-effective electricity to citizens. With an initial outlay of Rs. 9,400 crores, it aims to achieve a Levelized Cost of Storage (LCoS) ranging from Rs. 5.50-6.60 per kWh."
    },
    {
      "question": "22. As per a recent report, the coastal waters of which state are facing a ecological threat from the invasive Caribbean false mussel?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Kerala[B] Andhra Pradesh[C] Goa[D] Tamil Nadu"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Kerala]",
      "hint": "Notes:The coastal waters of Kerala are facing a significant ecological threat from the invasive Caribbean false mussel, as revealed by a report from the Intergovernmental Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (IPBES).\nThis invasive species, originally from South and Central America, has rapidly spread throughout Kerala’s coastal waters, displacing native clams and oysters crucial for the state’s fisheries."
    },
    {
      "question": "23. Which institution issued guidelines to strengthen cyber security and cyber resilience framework for stock exchanges?",
      "options": [
        "[A] RBI[B] SEBI[C] IRDAI[D] PFRDA"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [SEBI]",
      "hint": "Notes:SEBI issued guidelines to strengthen cyber security and cyber resilience framework for stock exchanges and other market infrastructure institutions (MIIs).\nAs per the guidelines, MIIs shall maintain offline, encrypted backups of data and shall regularly test these backups at least on a quarterly basis to ensure confidentiality, integrity and availability."
    },
    {
      "question": "24. Which company has introduced India’s first UPI-ATM in partnership with NPCI?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Hitachi[B] Paytm[C] Pine Labs[D] India1"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Hitachi]",
      "hint": "Notes:Hitachi Payment Services, a subsidiary of Japan-based Hitachi, introduced India’s first UPI-ATM in partnership with the National Payments Corporation of India (NPCI) during the Global Fintech Fest in Mumbai.\nThis UPI-ATM allows customers to withdraw cash without the need for a debit or credit card. The United Payments Interface (UPI) is a mobile payment method operated by NPCI that enables instant and free fund transfers between bank accounts."
    },
    {
      "question": "25. The Indian Army and Indian Air Force conducted a joint training exercise named?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Shravan[B] Nabh Shakti[C] Strike Shakti[D] Brahmastra"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Nabh Shakti]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Indian Army’s elite Brahmastra Corps in the Northeastern states recently conducted a joint training exercise called ‘Nabh Shakti,’ with participation from both the Indian Army and the Indian Air Force.\nThe Brahmastra Corps, also known as the 17 Mountain Strike Corps, has been established to carry out strike operations in enemy territory during conflicts in the eastern regions of India."
    },
    {
      "question": "26. A report by which institution has stated that the window to reach climate goals is ‘rapidly closing’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] UN[B] WHO[C] IMF[D] FAO"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [UN]",
      "hint": "Notes:A new report from the United Nations has emphasized the urgency of addressing climate change, stating that the window of opportunity to limit global temperature rise to 1.5 degrees Celsius above pre-industrial levels is rapidly closing.\nThe report, part of the Global Stock take (GST) mandated by the Paris Agreement, highlights that while some progress has been made, countries are far from achieving the necessary targets to meet this goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "27. NASA’s MOXIE Successfully Generated Oxygen on which planet?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Mars[B] Jupiter[C] Moon[D] Venus"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Mars]",
      "hint": "Notes:The US Space agency NASA has announced that its Mars Oxygen In-Situ Resource Utilization Experiment (MOXIE) which is on board the Perseverance Mars Rover has been successful in generating oxygen in Mars. The equipment demonstrated its ability to convert Martian carbon dioxide (CO2) into oxygen.\nThis technology breakthrough could play a crucial role in future human missions to Mars, providing a sustainable source of breathable air and rocket propellant."
    },
    {
      "question": "28. Which institution has released the report titled “India Real Estate: Vision 2047”?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Knight Frank India[B] Reserve Bank of India[C] National Housing Bank[D] Real Estate Association of India"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Knight Frank India]",
      "hint": "Notes:Knight Frank India in association with NAREDCO has released a report titled “India Real Estate: Vision 2047”. This report presents a comprehensive outlook on transformative trends in India’s real estate sector over the next 25 years.\nThe report states that real estate sector played a pivotal role in contributing to the revenue of Indian states and Union Territories. The sector has generated about Rs 2 lakh crore through stamp duties, registration fees, and land revenue."
    },
    {
      "question": "29. Which state has mandated Vehicle Location Tracking Devices for Commercial Vehicles?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Tamil Nadu[B] Kerala[C] Karnataka[D] Odisha"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: D [Odisha]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Odisha State Transport Authority (STA) has made it mandatory for all commercial vehicles, excluding three-wheelers, to install Vehicle Location Tracking (VLT) devices with panic buttons.\nThis decision, aimed at enhancing passenger safety, particularly for women and children, applies to all categories of new commercial vehicles, including buses, taxis, goods vehicles, and ambulances. The deadline for new vehicles to have these devices is October 1, with installation required at the time of registration. Older vehicles have until December 31 to comply."
    },
    {
      "question": "30. Mount Fuji is located in which country?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Tibet[B] China[C] Japan[D] Indonesia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Japan]",
      "hint": "Notes:The iconic Mount Fuji in Japan has witnessed a dramatic increase in visitors, with over 5.1 million tourists between 2012 and 2019.\nThis has led to concerns about ecological damage and safety risks to the mountain ecosystem. Visitors, including those climbing at night to witness the sunrise, have overwhelmed the region. Facilities catering to tourists rely on diesel generators, leading to environmental concerns, while overcrowding and breaches of etiquette have become common."
    },
    {
      "question": "31. India has reached out to which country to restock monoclonal antibody doses to combat the Nipah virus?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Australia[B] Japan[C] USA[D] Israel"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Australia]",
      "hint": "Notes:India has reached out to Australia to procure monoclonal antibody doses to combat the Nipah virus outbreak in Kerala. India is expecting 20 more doses soon, as per the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR).\nThe virus has killed two people so far and has infected at least five others in the Kozhikode district. The current Nipah outbreak is Kerala’s fourth since 2018."
    },
    {
      "question": "32. Burkina Faso’s military junta has ordered which country’s defence attache to leave?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Israel[B] UAE[C] France[D] Germany"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [France]",
      "hint": "Notes:Burkina Faso’s military junta has ordered the French embassy’s defence attache to leave the country due to “subversive” behaviour.\nAttache Emmanuel Pasquier’s expulsion is the latest sign of increasing tension between the West African nation -Burkina Faso and its former coloniser France since a military government seized power in two coups last year."
    },
    {
      "question": "33. Automobile employees of which country launched a massive targeted strike?",
      "options": [
        "[A] China[B] Japan[C] USA[D] India"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:Around 13,000 members of the United Auto Workers (UAW) union in the United States initiated a strike affecting General Motors, Ford Motor, and Stellantis (parent of Chrysler, Jeep, and Ram).\nThe strike follows the breakdown of negotiations over better pay raises and benefits. The UAW seeks a 40% wage increase over four years, restoration of cost-of-living adjustments, and pensions for all workers, among other demands."
    },
    {
      "question": "34. Which country is the host of the Asian Games 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Japan[B] China[C] India[D] Sri Lanka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [China]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Hangzhou Asian Games Village was inaugurated at Hangzhou, China in the presence of acting director general of the Olympic Council of Asia, Vinod Kumar Tiwari.\nThe 19th edition of the mega event will commence on September 23. The village will accommodate 20,000 people in three communities: Athletes’ Village, Media Village and Technical Officials’ Village."
    },
    {
      "question": "35. What is the rank of India in the ‘World Happiness Index 2023’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] 126[B] 121[C] 118[D] 108"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [126]",
      "hint": "Notes:India has been ranked 126th among 146 countries in the latest World Happiness Index for 2023. This decline in happiness levels is attributed to the country’s growing mental health crisis, exacerbated by the ongoing impact of the Covid-19 pandemic.\nRecent data reveals a significant surge in the sale of antidepressants and mood stabilizers in India, with a 41% increase from August 2019 to August 2023."
    },
    {
      "question": "36. Which institution introduced the National List of Essential Assistive Products (NLEAP)?",
      "options": [
        "[A] ICMR[B] IMA[C] AIIMS[D] NITI Aayog"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [ICMR]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) introduced the National List of Essential Assistive Products (NLEAP) to prioritize crucial assistive products for individuals with functional impairments. These assistive products are vital for enhancing the quality of life and promoting independence among individuals with disabilities. The NLEAP consists of 21 essential assistive products and technologies that are considered fundamental for improving the lives of those with functional impairments."
    },
    {
      "question": "37. Santiniketan, which was designated as a UNESCO World Heritage Site, is in which state?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Uttar Pradesh[B] West Bengal[C] Rajasthan[D] New Delhi"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [West Bengal]",
      "hint": "Notes:Santiniketan, the cultural and educational hub in West Bengal founded by poet Rabindranath Tagore, has been designated as a UNESCO World Heritage Site.\nThe announcement was made during the 45th session of the World Heritage Committee in Saudi Arabia. Established in 1901, Santiniketan was initially a residential school based on Indian traditions and the vision of global unity transcending religious and cultural boundaries. In 1921, it evolved into a world university known as ‘Visva Bharati’."
    },
    {
      "question": "38. ‘Khadi & Village Industries Commission’ functions under which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of MSME[B] Ministry of Commerce and Industry[C] Ministry of Culture[D] Ministry of Textiles"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of MSME]",
      "hint": "Notes:Khadi & Village Industries Commission signed MoUs with Prasar Bharati, NBCC (India) Limited, and Digital India Corporation. The objective of these MoUs is to prepare a roadmap to modernize the Khadi and Village Industries Commission and popularize its products among the youth.\nNBCC (India) Limited will build new modern infrastructure for Khadi and Village Industries Commission across the country."
    },
    {
      "question": "39. ‘Weather Information Network Data Systems (WINDS)’ is associated with which Union Ministry?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ministry of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare[B] Ministry of Cooperation[C] Ministry of Rural Development[D] Ministry of Environment, Forest and Climate Change"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Ministry of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Ministry of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare launched three initiatives, namely the Kisan Rin Portal (KRP), KCC Ghar Ghar Abhiyaan, an ambitious campaign aiming to extend the benefits of the Kisan Credit Card (KCC) Scheme to every farmer across the nation and a manual on Weather Information Network Data Systems (WINDS).\nUnion Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman and Union Agriculture Minister Narendra Singh Tomar unveiled initiatives focused on agri-credit (KCC & MISS) and crop insurance (PMFBY/RWBCIS)."
    },
    {
      "question": "40. As per a new study, Socio-political and ecological fragility threatens which species in Africa?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Lion[B] Elephant[C] Bee[D] Dog"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Lion]",
      "hint": "Notes:A new study, ‘Socio-political and ecological fragility of threatened, free-ranging African lion populations’ has found that socio-political factors are posing a significant threat to already fragile lion populations in Africa.\nThe study revealed that Somalian and Malawian lion populations are the most threatened when considering socio-political and ecological fragility. Ethiopia’s Maze National Park was identified as the most ecologically fragile geographic population."
    },
    {
      "question": "41. Which city hosted the Sustainable Development Goals (SDG) Summit in September 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] New Delhi[B] New York[C] Paris[D] Nairobi"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [New York]",
      "hint": "Notes:Leaders from around the world gathered at the UN-hosted High-level Sustainable Development Goals (SDG) Summit in New York and endorsed a resolute political declaration.\nThis declaration outlines their shared commitment to creating a sustainable and inclusive world by 2030. Leaders reiterated the importance of the Addis Ababa Action Agenda and called for swift action to implement the UN Secretary-General’s proposal for an SDG stimulus."
    },
    {
      "question": "42. India has partnered with which country to deploy 10,000 made-in-India electric buses across Indian cities?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Germany[B] Finland[C] USA[D] Australia"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [USA]",
      "hint": "Notes:India and the United States have initiated a collaboration to deploy 10,000 made-in-India electric buses across Indian cities.\nThis partnership, announced during Prime Minister Narendra Modi’s visit to the White House, focuses on expanding options for electric public transportation in India, fostering cleaner urban environments, and promoting healthier communities."
    },
    {
      "question": "43. Which Indian state signed MoU with the British Council for research, faculty, student exchange programmes?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Telangana[B] Tamil Nadu[C] Kerala[D] Karnataka"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Tamil Nadu]",
      "hint": "Notes:Tamil Nadu state government signed an agreement with the British Council for two-way student mobility, capacity building, research and transnational education.\nThe British Council would enable collaborations in new and emerging areas through ‘Going Global Partnerships’ that the state is already part of."
    },
    {
      "question": "44. Which airlines has received Indian Government’s nod to start international flights, in September 2023?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Spice Jet[B] Akasa Air[C] Go First[D] Air Deccan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Akasa Air]",
      "hint": "Notes:Mumbai-headquartered budget airlines Akasa Air has received the Union Government’s nod to start international flights, which is expected before the year-end.\nThe approval has been received despite mass flight cancellations in the past three months as more than 40 pilots walked out to join rival Tata-led Air India Express."
    },
    {
      "question": "45. Which country announced a strategic partnership with China, ahead of Asian Games?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Ukraine[B] Syria[C] Israel[D] UAE"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Syria]",
      "hint": "Notes:China and Syria announced the formation of a strategic partnership as Chinese leader Xi Jinping kicked off a series of diplomatic meetings ahead of the upcoming Asian Games.\nThe Syrian leader attended the Asian Games opening ceremony along with the king of Cambodia, the crown prince of Kuwait and the prime ministers of Nepal, East Timor and South Korea."
    },
    {
      "question": "46. Which state has launched its ‘Action Plan for Management of Paddy Stubble Burning’?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Punjab[B] Haryana[C] Uttar Pradesh[D] Rajasthan"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [Haryana]",
      "hint": "Notes:Haryana submitted its ‘State Action Plan for Management of Paddy Stubble Burning’ to Commission for Air Quality Management (CAQM).\nIn the plan, Haryana aims to significantly reduce and potentially eliminate fire incidents resulting from paddy stubble burning this year. To achieve this, the state plans to implement bio-decomposer applications in 5 lakh acres of land during the current harvesting season."
    },
    {
      "question": "47. The Indian Navy (IN) signed MoU with which institution for Defense Technology Collaboration?",
      "options": [
        "[A] IIT Madras[B] IISc Bengaluru[C] IIT Delhi[D] IIT BHU"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: B [IISc Bengaluru]",
      "hint": "Notes:The Indian Navy and the Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bengaluru, have signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) to collaborate on technical research and development in various engineering fields related to defense technologies.\nThe MoU aims to promote academic cooperation, enhance scientific understanding, and facilitate capacity building, equipment development, and faculty exchange between the two organizations."
    },
    {
      "question": "48. Congestion Tax is set to be launched in which Indian city?",
      "options": [
        "[A] New Delhi[B] Mumbai[C] Bengaluru[D] Kolkata"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Bengaluru]",
      "hint": "Notes:A congestion tax is set to be introduced during rush hours on nine designated routes in Bengaluru. This is an effort to ease traffic congestion in the city with an aim to discourage the use of private vehicles and promote the use of public transportation.\nIt is estimated that Bengaluru suffers a loss of ₹19,725 crore per year due to traffic delays, congestion, stoppage of signals, time loss, fuel loss and related factors."
    },
    {
      "question": "49. Which equipment is used to split water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen by utilizing electricity?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Electrolysers[B] Neutralisers[C] Electrolytes[D] Water splitter"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: A [Electrolysers]",
      "hint": "Notes:Electrolysers are instruments employed in the industrial process of splitting water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen by utilizing electricity generated from renewable sources like solar, wind, or nuclear power.\nAccording to a recent report by the International Energy Agency, China is expected to have authority over 50% of the global installed capacity of electrolysers for low-carbon hydrogen production by the conclusion of 2023, despite a decrease in new projects due to rising inflation."
    },
    {
      "question": "50. Tamil Nadu Public Health Act has been invoked for control of which communicable disease?",
      "options": [
        "[A] Typhoid[B] Covid[C] Dengue[D] Chicken Pox"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Correct Answer: C [Dengue]",
      "hint": "Notes:In the wake of a surge in dengue fever cases in Tamil Nadu, the Directorate of Public Health (DPH) and Preventive Medicine of the state has invoked provisions of the Tamil Nadu Public Health Act 1939, for control of the disease.\nFailure to report a notifiable disease, failure to comply with notices requiring measures against mosquito breeding or interrupting mosquito control work would attract penalties under the Act."
    }
  ],
  "type": "current-affairs-quiz-september-2023",
  "__v": 0
}]